<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse shewing who they are that are now qualify'd to administer baptism and the Lord's-Supper wherein the cause of episcopacy is briefly treated / by the author of A discourse proving the divine institution of water-baptism.</title>
            <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25145</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08780596</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08780596</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41791</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47742)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41791)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1262:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse shewing who they are that are now qualify'd to administer baptism and the Lord's-Supper wherein the cause of episcopacy is briefly treated / by the author of A discourse proving the divine institution of water-baptism.</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for C. Brome W. Keblewhite and H. Hindmarsh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes text in Greek and Latin.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 62.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
               <term>Episcopacy.</term>
               <term>Sacraments.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41791:1"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE; SHEWING, Who they are that are now Qualify'd to Adminiſter <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lord's-Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein the Cauſe of EPISCOPACY Is briefly Treated.</p>
            <p>By the Author OF A DISCOURSE Proving the Divine Inſtitution of <hi>Water-Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>No Man taketh this Honour unto himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Heb. 5.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>C. Brome</hi> at the <hi>Gun,</hi> at Weſt-end of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s; <hi>W. Keble white</hi> at the <hi>Swan</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard; and <hi>H. Hindmarſh</hi> at the <hi>Golden-Ball</hi> over-againſt the Royal Exchange, <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:41791:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41791:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THIS <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> was Promis'd in that which I formerly Publiſh'd, proving the <hi>Divine Inſtitution</hi> of <hi>Water-Baptiſm;</hi> And was intended to have been Annex'd to that, but ſome Delays prevented it.</p>
            <p>I can give no good Reaſon why it has ſtay'd thus long, having made but little Addition to what was then done: But other things Interven'd, and, as it is uſual in Delays, the firſt in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign proves the laſt in Fact.</p>
            <p>The Subject of this has led me direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the larger Theme of <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> which having been ſo <hi>Elaboratly</hi> and ſo <hi>Often</hi> treated of, I intend not in this to Branch out into ſo wide a Field; but in a short compendious Method, to lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and others of our <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:41791:3"/>from <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> the Heart of the Cauſe, ſo far particularly as it concerns our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Subject, the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Admimiſtring</hi> the <hi>Sacraments</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to avoid the length of Quotations, when brought into the Diſcourſe, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated upon, I have, at the end, Annex'd a ſmall <hi>Index</hi> of Quotations out of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> of the firſt 450 Years after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to which the Reader may Recur, as ther is occaſion. And having them all in one view, may conſider them more Intirely, and Remember them the better.</p>
            <p>I have Tranſlated them for the ſake of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reader, but have put the <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals</hi> in another <hi>Column,</hi> to juſtifie the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation; and for their ſakes who may not have the Books at hand.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:41791:3"/>
            <head>The CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. I.</hi> The Neceſſity of an <hi>Outward</hi> Commiſſion to the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>The Caſe is Stated, as to thoſe <hi>Quakers,</hi> for whoſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction this is Intended. <hi>Page 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Of <hi>Perſonal</hi> Qualifications requiſite in the <hi>Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments. Page 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Of the <hi>Sacerdotal</hi> Qualification of an <hi>Outward</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, as was given to <hi>Chriſt</hi> by <hi>God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> By <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> By the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to others.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Thoſe others Impower'd to give it to others after them.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> The Deduction of this <hi>Commiſſion</hi> is continu'd in the Succeſſion of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and not of <hi>Presbyters.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Either way it operates againſt the <hi>Quakers. Page 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> The Continuance of every <hi>Society</hi> is Deduc'd in the <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> of the <hi>Chief Governours</hi> of the Society, not of the <hi>Inferior Officers. Page 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> This ſhewn, in Matter of Fact, as to the <hi>Church</hi> and the Succeſſion of <hi>Biſhops</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times to our Days; particularly here in <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> The <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Plea conſider'd, that <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> were but ſingle <hi>Pariſhes;</hi> and conſequently, that every <hi>Presbyter</hi> was a <hi>Biſhop;</hi> and their vain <hi>Logo-machy</hi> upon the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Page 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Argu'd from the Type of the <hi>Levitical</hi> Prieſthood, which ſhewn to be the Method of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Fathers. Page 7</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:41791:4"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Whence the Caſe of <hi>Korah</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſhewn to be the ſame. And the <hi>Epiſcopal Supremacy</hi> as Plainly and Fully Eſtabliſhed, as was that of <hi>Aaron</hi> and his <hi>Succeſſors. Page 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> No <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of <hi>Presbyters</hi> can be ſhewn from the <hi>Apoſtles. Page 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> The Pretence of Extraordinary <hi>Gifts,</hi> no Ground or Excuſe for making of a <hi>Schiſm. Page 11</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> Objection from the Times of <hi>Popery</hi> in this Kingdom; as if that did <hi>Un-church,</hi> and conſequently break the <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> of our <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> This ſhewn to be a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Argument. <hi>Page 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> That <hi>Idolatry</hi> does not <hi>Un-church.</hi> Prov'd
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Becauſe a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> may be an <hi>Idolater. Page 18</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> From the Type of the <hi>Church</hi> under the <hi>Law. Page 19</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III. Epiſcopacy</hi> the moſt oppoſite to <hi>Popery. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV. Male-Adminiſtration</hi> does <hi>Forfeit,</hi> but not <hi>Vacate</hi> a <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> till it be Re-call'd. <hi>Page 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Defects in <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> no Bar to the <hi>Poſſeſſors,</hi> where ther are none who <hi>Claim</hi> a <hi>Better Right. Page 23</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> The <hi>Aſſurance</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> in the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, beyond that of any other.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> The <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Communion of much greater Extent, and more <hi>Univerſal</hi> than all thoſe who oppoſe it. <hi>Page 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> And than the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> if join'd with them. <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> The <hi>Diſſenters</hi> from <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> do all Deny the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> or <hi>Call</hi> of each other. <hi>Page 25</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:41791:4"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> If the <hi>Quakers</hi> receive <hi>Baptiſm</hi> from any of theſe <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters,</hi> they have no Reaſon to expect the ſame Allowan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as may be given to thoſe of their own Communions.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> The Epiſcopal Ordinations, and conſequently their Right to <hi>Baptize,</hi> is own'd by both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Prerbyterians.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> The <hi>Perſonal Sanctity</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrator</hi> of the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> tho' highly Requiſit on his Part, yet not of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,</hi> as to the <hi>Receivers,</hi> to convey to them the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of the <hi>Sacraments:</hi> Becauſe</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> The <hi>Vertue</hi> comes not from the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> but from <hi>God</hi> alone. <hi>Page 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> For this Cauſe (among others) <hi>Chriſt</hi> choſe <hi>Judas</hi> to be an <hi>Apoſtle. Page 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III. God</hi>'s Power is Magnify'd in the <hi>Meaneſs</hi> of His <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> Rejoyc'd at the <hi>Preaching</hi> of <hi>Evil</hi> Men <hi>Page 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> This confirm'd by dayly Experience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> The Argument ſtronger as to the <hi>Sacraments. Page 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> The Fatal Conſequences of making the <hi>Perſonal Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrator</hi> Neceſſary towards the <hi>Efficacy</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> It takes away all <hi>Aſſurance</hi> in our Receiving of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> It renders the Commands of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of none Effect. <hi>Page 30</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> It is contrary to the tenure of <hi>God</hi>'s former Inſtitutions; and puts us in a more uncertain Condition than they were under the <hi>Law.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> It was the Ancient Error of the <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> and Borders upon <hi>Popery.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:41791:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> As great <hi>Sanctity</hi> to be found in the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as among any of our <hi>Diſſenters. Page 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IX.</hi> Ther is, at leaſt, a <hi>Doubt,</hi> in Receiving <hi>Baptiſm</hi> from any of our <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> Which, in this caſe, is a <hi>Sin:</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ſecurity</hi> is only to be had in the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Communion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>X.</hi> The Advantage of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by Her being the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Conſtitution,</hi> ever ſince, the <hi>Reformation.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> That therefore nothing can excuſe <hi>Schiſm</hi> from Her, but Her <hi>Enjoyning</hi> ſomething, as a <hi>Condition</hi> of <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> that is contrary to the Holy <hi>Scriptures;</hi> which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhewn. <hi>Page 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> Therefore to Receive <hi>Baptlſm</hi> from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is the greateſt <hi>ſecurity</hi> which the <hi>Quakers</hi> can have of Receiving it from Proper Hands.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> An <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Objection,</hi> That <hi>Baptiſm</hi> has not ſuch <hi>Viſible Effects</hi> amongſt us, as the <hi>Quakers</hi> wou'd deſire. <hi>Page 34</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Supplement.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Some <hi>Authorities</hi> for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as <hi>Diſtinct</hi> from, and <hi>Superior</hi> to <hi>Presbytery,</hi> taken out of the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> in the firſt <hi>450</hi> Years after <hi>Chriſt. Page 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> That the whole <hi>Reformation;</hi> even <hi>Calvin, Beza,</hi> and thoſe of their <hi>Communion,</hi> were zealous <hi>Aſſerters</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy. Page 58</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41791:5"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE <hi>Shewing, who they are that are now qualify'd to Adminiſter</hi> BAPTISM, <hi>and the</hi> LORD's SUPPER.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>The Neceſſity of an</hi> Outward <hi>Commiſſion to the</hi> Miniſters <hi>of the</hi> Goſpel.</head>
               <p>SOme <hi>Quakers</hi> having perus'd my <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> think the <hi>Quaker</hi> Arguments againſt it ſufficiently Anſwered: And they have but one Difficulty remaining, that is, who they are (among the various Pretenders) that are duly Qualify'd to <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter</hi> it.</p>
               <p>And if ſatisfaction can be given to them herein, they promiſe a perfect Compliance to that <hi>Holy Inſtitution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Chief thing they ſeem to ſtand upon is the <hi>Perſonal Holyneſs</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrator;</hi> thinking that the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Effects of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> cannot be convey'd by the means of an <hi>Unſanctify'd Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet they Confeſs, that there is ſomething elſe Neceſſary, beſides the <hi>Perſonal Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrator:</hi> Otherwiſe, they wou'd think themſelves as much <hi>Qualify'd</hi> to <hi>Adminiſter</hi> it as any others; becauſe, I preſume, they ſuppoſe themſelves to have as great a Meaſure of the <hi>Spirit</hi> as other Men.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Requiſit</hi> which they want, is that of <hi>Lawful Ordination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Presbyterians, Independents,</hi> and <hi>Baptiſts</hi> do pretend to this. Therefore their <hi>Title</hi> to it is to be Examin'd.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:41791:6"/>
               <p>And, that we may proceed the more clearly in this Matter, with Reſpect ſtill to that Difficulty upon which the <hi>Quakers</hi> lay the ſtreſs; we will Inquire concerning thoſe <hi>Qualifications</hi> which are Requiſit in any Perſon that ſhall take upon him to <hi>Adminiſter</hi> the <hi>Sacraments</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Inſtitution. And,</p>
               <p>Theſe Qualifications are of two ſorts, <hi>Perſonal</hi> or <hi>Sacerdotal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Perſonal.</hi> The <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrator.</hi> And, though this is a great Qualification to <hi>Fit</hi> and <hi>Prepare</hi> a Man for ſuch an Holy Adminiſtration, yet this <hi>Alone</hi> does not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently Qualifie any Man to take upon him ſuch an Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration.</p>
               <p n="2">II. But there is moreover requir'd, 2ly. A <hi>Sacerdotal</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification, that is, an <hi>Outward Commiſſion,</hi> to Authorize a Man to execute any <hi>Sacerdotal</hi> or <hi>Miniſterial</hi> Act of Religion. For, <hi>This Honour no Man taketh unto himſelf, but he that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of God,
<note place="margin">Heb. v. 4.</note> as was</hi> Aaron; <hi>ſo alſo Chriſt glorify'd not himſelf to be made an High-Prieſt; But he that ſaid unto him, thou art my Son—Thou art a Prieſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Accordingly we find that <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not take upon Him the Office of a <hi>Preacher,</hi> till after that <hi>Outward Commiſſion</hi> given to Him by a <hi>Voice</hi> from <hi>Heaven,</hi> at His <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> for it is written, <hi>Matth.</hi> iv. 17. <hi>From that time</hi> Jeſus <hi>began to Preach:</hi> Then He <hi>Began;</hi> and He was then <hi>about Thirty Years of Age,</hi> Luke iii. 23. Now no Man can doubt of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Qualifications, before <hi>that time,</hi> as to <hi>Holineſs, Sufficiency,</hi> and all <hi>Perſonal</hi> Endowments. And if all theſe were not ſufficient to <hi>Christ</hi> Himſelf, without an <hi>Outward Commiſſion,</hi> what other Man can pretend to it upon the Account of any <hi>Perſonal</hi> Excellencies in Himſelf, without an <hi>outward Commiſſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. And as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was outwardly Commiſſionated by <hi>His Father,</hi> ſo did not He leave it to His Diſciples, every ones Opinion of his own ſufficiency, to thruſt himſelf into the <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> but Choſe Twelve <hi>Apoſtles</hi> by Name; and after them, Seventy others of an Inferior Order, whom He ſent to <hi>Preach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. And as <hi>Christ</hi> gave <hi>outward Commiſſions,</hi> while He was upon the Earth,
<note place="margin">Act. xiv. 23.</note> ſo we find that His <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the ſame Method, after His Aſcenſion. <hi>They ordained them Elders in every Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. But had they, who were thus Ordained by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41791:6"/>Power to Ordain others? Yes,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.5 1 Tim. v 22.</note> 
                  <hi>For this cauſe left I thee in</hi> Crete, <hi>that thou ſhouldeſt — Ordain Elders in every City. Lay hands ſuddenly on no Man,</hi> &amp;c. St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in his firſt <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> writing concerning the <hi>Schiſm</hi> which was then riſen up amongſt them, ſays, Parag. 44.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Apoſtles fore-knowing there wou'd be Conteſts concerning the Epiſcopal Name (or Office) did themſelves appoint the Perſons:</hi> And not only ſo, leſt that might be ſaid to be of force, only during their time. But that they <hi>afterwards eſtabliſhed an Order how, when thoſe whom they had Ordained ſhou'd Die; others, fit and approved Men, ſhou'd ſucceed them in their Miniſtry.</hi> Par. 43. <hi>that they who were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with this Work, by God, in Chriſt, did Conſtitute theſe Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this Matter depends not upon the Teſtimony of him, or many more that might be produced. It is ſuch a Publick Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Fact; That I might as well go about to quote particular Authors, to prove that there were <hi>Emperors</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> as that the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> were <hi>Ordained</hi> to ſucceed one another; and that they did ſo ſucceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>The Deduction of this</hi> Commiſſion <hi>is continu'd in the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of</hi> Biſhops <hi>and not of</hi> Presbyters.</head>
               <p>BUT here is a Diſpute, whether this <hi>Succeſſion</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd in the Order of <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Presbyters?</hi> or whether both are not the ſame?</p>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This is the Conteſt betwixt the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and us: But either way it operates againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who allow of no <hi>Succeſſion</hi> deriv'd by <hi>outward Ordination.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:41791:7"/>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. But becauſe the Deſign of this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> is to ſhew the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> I anſwer that this <hi>Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> is preſerv'd and deriv'd only in the <hi>Biſhops:</hi> As the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of any <hi>Society,</hi> is deduc'd in the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Chief Governors</hi> of the <hi>Society,</hi> not of the <hi>Inferior Officers.</hi> Thus in Kingdoms, we reckon by the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Kings,</hi> not of <hi>Sheriffs</hi> or <hi>Conſtables;</hi> and in <hi>Corporations</hi> by the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Mayors</hi> or other <hi>Chief Officers;</hi> not of the Inferiour <hi>Bailiffs</hi> or <hi>Serjeants:</hi> So the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Churches</hi> is Computed in the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who are the <hi>Chief Governours</hi> of the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches;</hi> and not of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> who are but <hi>Inferiour Officers</hi> under the <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. And, in this, the Matter of Fact is as Clear and Evident as the Succeſſion of any <hi>Kings</hi> or <hi>Corporations</hi> in the World.</p>
               <p>To begin with the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> we find not only that they Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted <hi>Timothy</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> of <hi>Crete,</hi> as in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles to them: But, in <hi>Euſebius</hi> and other <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtorians,</hi> you have the <hi>Biſhops</hi> Nam'd who were Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by the Apoſtles themſelves, over the then famous Churches of <hi>Jeruſalem, Antioch, Rome,</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and many other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of them down all along.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Polycarp,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> was Diſciple to St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Apoſtle;</hi> and St. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who was Diſciple to St. <hi>Polycarp,</hi> was Conſtituted <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lyons</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I mention this, becauſe it is ſo near us; for, in all other <hi>Churches,</hi> throughout the whole World, where ever <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> was Planted, <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> was every where Eſtabliſh'd, without one Exception, as is Evident from all their Records.</p>
               <p>And ſo it was with us in <hi>England,</hi> whither it is generally ſuppos'd, and with very good Grounds, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> firſt brought the Chriſtian Faith. <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> in his <hi>Firſt Epiſt.</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> Paragr. 5. Says, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> went Preaching the Goſpel to the fartheſt bounds of the <hi>Weſt;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. by which Term <hi>Britain</hi> was then Underſtood. And <hi>Theodoret</hi> expreſly Names the <hi>Britains</hi> among the Nations Converted by the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> (To. 4. ſerm. 9. p. 610.) And <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Demonſtration,</hi> (l. 3. c. 7. p. 113.) Names likewiſe the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> as then Converted.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41791:7"/>
               <p>But whether St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or, as ſome Conjecture, <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathea,</hi> or any other <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Perſon was the firſt who Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> it matters not, as to our Preſent Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; who Enquire only concerning <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> And it is Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain by all our Hiſtories; that as far up as they give us any Account of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in this <hi>Iſland,</hi> they tell us likewiſe of <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and the Succeſſion of this <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> has been Deduc'd in the Succeſſion of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and not of <hi>Presbyters.</hi> And particularly in the <hi>Dioceſs</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> which was the firſt <hi>Archi-Epiſcopal See,</hi> before <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the <hi>Monk</hi> came hither, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which it was Eſtabliſh'd in <hi>Canterbury.</hi> And the <hi>Saxon</hi> Writers have Tranſmitted the Succeſſion of their <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, Rocheſter, London,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And in Countries ſo Remote and Barbarous as <hi>Iſland</hi> it ſelf we find the ſame care taken; <hi>Ara</hi> or <hi>Aras</hi> an <hi>Iſlandiſh</hi> Prieſt Surnam'd <hi>Hinfrode</hi> the <hi>Leurned,</hi> who flouriſh'd in the <hi>Eleventh Century,</hi> and was 25 Years Old when <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> was brought thither, in his Book of that Country written in <hi>Iſlandiſh,</hi> has Tranſmitted to Poſterity, not only the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> but the <hi>Genea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Skalholt</hi> and <hi>Hola</hi> (the two Epiſcopal Sees of <hi>Iſland</hi>) as they Succeeded one another in his Time. I mention this of <hi>Iſland,</hi> to ſhow that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> has Extended it ſelf Equally with <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which was carry'd by it, into the Remoteſt Corners of the Earth; upon which account the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Skalholt</hi> and <hi>Hola,</hi> and their <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> are as Remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Proofs of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> tho' not ſo Famous as the Biſhops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>London.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">IV. If the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will ſay (becauſe they have nothing left to ſay) that all <hi>London</hi> (for Example) was but one <hi>Pariſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and that the <hi>Presbyter</hi> of every other <hi>Pariſh</hi> was as much a <hi>Biſhop</hi> as the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London;</hi> becauſe the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> are ſometimes us'd in the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> They may as well prove that <hi>Christ</hi> was but a <hi>Deacon,</hi> becauſe He is ſo call'd, <hi>Rom.</hi> xv. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which we rightly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are a <hi>Miniſter:</hi> And <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſignifies an <hi>Overſeer,</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> an <hi>Ancient Man,</hi> or <hi>Elder Man;</hi> whence our Term of <hi>Alderm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> And this is as good a Foundation to Prove that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were <hi>Aldermen,</hi> in the <hi>City</hi> acceptation of the Word; or that our <hi>Aldermen</hi> are all <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as to Prove that <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:41791:8"/>and <hi>Biſhops</hi> are all one, from the Childiſh <hi>Gingle</hi> of the Words.</p>
               <p>It wou'd be the ſame thing, if one ſhou'd undertake to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front all Antiquity, and Prove againſt all the Hiſtories, that the <hi>Emperors</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> were no more than <hi>Generals</hi> of <hi>Armies,</hi> and that every Roman <hi>General</hi> was <hi>Emperor</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> becauſe he cou'd find the word <hi>Imperator</hi> ſometimes apply'd to the <hi>General</hi> of an <hi>Army.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or as if a <hi>Common-wealth-man</hi> ſhou'd get up, and ſay, that our former <hi>Kings</hi> were no more than our <hi>Dukes</hi> are now; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Stile of <hi>Grace,</hi> which is now given to <hi>Dukes,</hi> was then given to <hi>Kings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſuppoſe that any one were put under the Pennance of Anſwering to ſuch Ridiculous Arguments; what Method wou'd he take, but to ſhew that the <hi>Emperors</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and former <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> had <hi>Generals</hi> of <hi>Armies</hi> and <hi>Dukes</hi> under them, and Exercis'd Authority over them?</p>
               <p>Therefore when we find it given in Charge to <hi>Timothy,</hi> the firſt <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> how he was to Proceed againſt his <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> when they Tranſgreſſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to Sit in <hi>Judgment</hi> upon them, Examine <hi>Witneſſes</hi> againſt them, and paſs <hi>Cenſures</hi> upon them, it is a moſt Impertinent <hi>Logo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>chy</hi> to argue from the <hi>Etymology</hi> of the Words, that notwithſtanding of all this, a <hi>Biſhop</hi> and a <hi>Presbyter</hi> are the ſame thing. Therefore that one Text, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> v. 19. is ſufficient to ſilence this Pitiful Clamour of the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians;</hi> our <hi>Engliſh</hi> reads it, <hi>againſt an Elder,</hi> which is the <hi>Literal</hi> Tranſlation of the word <hi>Presbyter, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, againſt a</hi> Presbyter <hi>receive not an Accuſation, but before two or three Witneſſes,</hi> and, <hi>them that ſin Rebuke before all, that others alſo may fear.</hi> Now, upon the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Hypotheſis, we muſt ſay that <hi>Timothy</hi> had no <hi>Authority</hi> or <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> over that <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter,</hi> againſt whom he had Power to Receive <hi>Accuſations,</hi> Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> and paſs <hi>Cenſures</hi> upon him: And that ſuch a <hi>Presbyter</hi> had the ſame <hi>Authority</hi> over <hi>Timothy</hi>— which is ſo Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant and againſt Common Senſe, that I will not ſtay lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to Confute it; and think this enough to have ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Argument from the <hi>Etymology</hi> of the words <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41791:8"/>
               <p>And this likewiſe Confutes their other <hi>Pretence,</hi> which I have mention'd, that the Ancient <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> were only <hi>Single</hi> and <hi>Independent Congregations,</hi> or <hi>Pariſhes.</hi> This is a <hi>Topick</hi> they have taken up but of late (being Beaten from all their other Holds) and Launched by Mr. <hi>David Clarkſon,</hi> in a Book which he Entitules <hi>Primitive Epiſcopacy;</hi> which has given occaſion to an Excellent Anſwer, by Dr. <hi>Hen. Maurice,</hi> call'd <hi>A Defence of Dioceſan Epiſcopacy,</hi> Printed 1691. which, I ſuppoſe, has ended that Controverſie, and hindred the World from being more troubl'd upon that Head. And their other little Shift, and as Groundleſs, that the Primitive <hi>Biſhops</hi> were no other than their <hi>Moderators,</hi> advanced more lately by <hi>Gilb. Rule</hi> late <hi>Moderator</hi> of the <hi>General Aſſembly</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> has been as <hi>Learnedly,</hi> and with great Clearneſs of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Confuted by the Worthy <hi>J. S.</hi> in his <hi>Principles of the Cyprianick Age,</hi> Printed 1695.</p>
               <p>But, as I ſaid, that Text, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> v. 19. has made all theſe <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> wholly uſeleſs to the <hi>Presbyterians:</hi> For ſuppoſing their moſt Notorious falſe ſuppoſition, as if the <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Rome, Alexandria,</hi> or <hi>London,</hi> conſiſted but of one ſingle Congregation, and that ſuch <hi>Biſhops</hi> had no <hi>Presbyters</hi> under them; but that all <hi>Presbyters</hi> were Equally <hi>Biſhops;</hi> I ſay, ſuppoſing this, then it muſt follow from what we Read of <hi>Timothy,</hi> that one <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Presbyter</hi> had <hi>Juriſdicton</hi> over other <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> which will Deſtroy the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Claim of <hi>Parity,</hi> as much as their Confeſſion to the <hi>Truth,</hi> and plain <hi>Matter of Fact,</hi> that <hi>Biſhops</hi> had <hi>Presbyters</hi> under their <hi>Juriſdiction;</hi> and that they were Diſtinct <hi>Orders:</hi> Notwithſtanding that a <hi>Biſhop</hi> may be call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>Deacon,</hi> or <hi>Miniſter</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and likewiſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an <hi>Elder</hi> or <hi>Grave</hi> Man, which is a Term of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy</hi> and <hi>Dignity,</hi> and not ty'd to <hi>Age.</hi> And a <hi>Presbyter</hi> may likewiſe, in a ſound Senſe, be call'd a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> that is, an <hi>Overſeer</hi> or <hi>Shepherd,</hi> which he truly is over his Particular Flock; without denying at all his Dependance upon his <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Overſeer:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. As under the Term of <hi>Prieſt,</hi> the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> was Included, without Deſtroying his <hi>Supremacy,</hi> over the other <hi>Prieſts.</hi> Againſt which <hi>Korah</hi> and his <hi>Presbyters,</hi> or Inferiour <hi>Prieſts</hi> aroſe. And if the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will take his word, whom, of all the Fathers, they moſt Admire, and Quote often on their ſide, that is, St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> he will tell them, in that very <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41791:9"/>(ad <hi>Evagr.</hi>) which they Boaſt favours them ſo much, That what <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his <hi>Sons,</hi> and the <hi>Levites</hi> were in the <hi>Temple,</hi> that ſame are <hi>Biſhop, Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Deacon</hi> in the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And long before him, <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> in his 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> makes frequent Alluſion to the <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> of the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical Prieſthood,</hi> and argues from thence to that of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church. Thus <hi>Paragraph</hi> 40.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>To the High-Prieſt</hi> (ſays he) <hi>were allotted his proper Offices; to the Prieſts, their proper place was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned; and to the Levites their ſervices were appointed; and the Lay-men were Reſtrain'd within the precepts to Lay-men.</hi> And <hi>Paragraph</hi> 42. he applies that Scripture, <hi>Iſa. LX.</hi> 17. to the Officers of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, and renders it thus; <hi>I will Conſtitute their</hi> Biſhops <hi>in Righteouſneſs, and their</hi> Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons <hi>in Faith.</hi> The <hi>Greek</hi> Tranſlation of the LXX has it thus. <hi>I will give thee Rulers</hi> (or Princes) <hi>in Peace;
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and thy</hi> Biſhops <hi>in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was the frequent Method of theſe Primitive Fathers to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus from the Parallel 'twixt the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the one being an Exact <hi>Type</hi> of the other, and therefore being fulfill'd in the other. And in this they follow'd the Example of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> who argu'd in the ſame manner, as you may ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> v. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> x. the whole <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> and many other Places of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">VI. Now the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are deſir'd to ſhew any one Diſpari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty betwixt their Caſe and that of <hi>Korah;</hi> who was a <hi>Priest</hi> of the <hi>ſecond</hi> Order, that is, a <hi>Presbyter;</hi> and withdrew his Obedience from the <hi>High-Priest</hi> with other Mutinous <hi>Levites:</hi> For, ther was no matter of <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Worſhip</hi> betwixt them and <hi>Aaron;</hi> nor any other Diſpute but that of <hi>Church-Government.</hi> And, by the Parallel betwixt the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> and the <hi>New, Korah</hi> was a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> who Roſe up againſt the <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> of <hi>Aaron.</hi> But this Caſe is brought yet nearer home; for, we are told (<hi>Jude</hi> xi.) of thoſe under the <hi>Goſpel, who periſh in the gain-ſaying of Korah:</hi> And in the <hi>Epist.</hi> of <hi>Clem. Rom.</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> before Quoted, <hi>Paragraph</hi> 43. He plainly applys this Caſe of <hi>Korah,</hi> to the ſtate of the <hi>Chriſtian Church;</hi> ſhewing at large, that as <hi>Moſes,</hi> by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41791:9"/>Command of God, Determin'd the Pretenſions of the Twelve <hi>Tribes</hi> to the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> by the Miraculous Budding of <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod, which was after the <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Puniſhment</hi> of <hi>Korah</hi> and his Company. <hi>So likewiſe,</hi> he ſays, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowing, by <hi>Christ,</hi> that Diſſentions wou'd ariſe alſo in the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> by various Pretenders to the <hi>Evangelical Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> did Settle and Eſtabliſh, not only the Perſons themſelves; But gave <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> for continuing the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> after their Deaths, as I have before Quoted his Words. So that it is plain from hence, That the <hi>Evangelical Prieſthood,</hi> is as <hi>Poſitively,</hi> and <hi>Certainly</hi> Eſtabliſh'd, and Determin'd, in the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Ordination,</hi> as the <hi>Levitical</hi> was, in the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of <hi>Aaron.</hi> And conſequently, that the <hi>Rebellion</hi> of <hi>Presbyters</hi> from under the Government of their <hi>Biſhops,</hi> is the ſame Caſe as the <hi>Rebellion</hi> (for ſo it is call'd, <hi>Numb.</hi> xvii. 10.) of <hi>Korah</hi> and his <hi>Levites,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Aaron;</hi> who had as good a Pretence againſt him from the word <hi>Levite,</hi> which was Common to the whole <hi>Tribe;</hi> as the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have againſt <hi>Biſhops,</hi> from the Name <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter,</hi> being us'd ſometimes promiſcuouſly, and apply'd to the <hi>Clergy</hi> in General; which is a Term that Includes all the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as <hi>Levite</hi> did among the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">VII. But, to leave the fruitleſs Conteſt about <hi>Words,</hi> let this Matter be Determin'd, as other Matters of Fact are.</p>
               <p>If I pretend to ſucceed any Man in an <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Eſtate,</hi> I muſt name him who had ſuch an <hi>Eſtate</hi> or <hi>Honour</hi> before me; and the Man who had it before him; and who had it before him; and ſo up all the way to him who firſt had it; and from whom all the reſt do derive; and how it was lawfully deduc'd from one to another.</p>
               <p>This the <hi>Biſhops</hi> have done, as I have ſhewn; and can name all the way backward, as far as Hiſtory goes, from the Preſent <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> (for example) to the firſt Plantation of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> in this Kingdom: So, from the preſent <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Lyons</hi> up to <hi>Irenaeus</hi> the Diſciple of St. <hi>Polycarp,</hi> as before is told. The Records are yet more certain in the Great <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> of <hi>Rome, Antioch, Alexandria,</hi> and others, while they laſted in the World. And tho' the Records may not be Extant of every ſmall <hi>Biſhoprick,</hi> which was leſs taken notice of; as the Names of many <hi>Kings</hi> are loſt, in obſcure Nations; of many <hi>Mayors</hi> or <hi>Sheriffs,</hi> who, notwithſtanding have as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41791:10"/>Succeeded one another, as where the Records are Preſerv'd. I ſay, tho' every <hi>Biſhop</hi> in the World cannot tell the Names of all his <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> up to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> yet their <hi>Succeſſion</hi> is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: And in moſt Chriſtian Nations there are <hi>Biſhops</hi> who can do it; which is a ſufficient Proof for the reſt, all ſtanding upon the ſame Bottom, and being Deriv'd in the ſame Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               <p>Now, to Ballance this, it is Deſir'd, that the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> wou'd ſhew the Succeſſion of any one <hi>Presbyter</hi> in the World, who was not likewiſe a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> in our acceptation of the Word, in the like manner, from the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Till when, their ſmall <hi>Criticiſms</hi> upon the <hi>Etymology</hi> of the Words, <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Presbyter,</hi> is as poor a Plea, as if I ſhou'd pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be Heir to an Eſtate, from the likeneſs of my Name to ſomebody who once had it.</p>
               <p>And here I cannot chooſe but apply the Complaint of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, John</hi> v. 43. If any come, in the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is, by a Commiſſion from Him, deriv'd down all the way, by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <hi>Ordination,</hi> him ye will not Receive: Nay, tho' he be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe a Man without Exception, either as to his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,</hi> or as to his <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Sufficiency</hi> for the <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> you make this his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> an <hi>Objection</hi> againſt him: For that <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alone,</hi> you will not accept him. But, if another come in <hi>his own Name,</hi> that is, with no <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> but what he has from himſelf; his <hi>own Opinion</hi> of his <hi>own Worthineſs; giving out that himſelf is ſome Great One,</hi> (Act. viii. 9.) him ye will Receive, and Follow and Admire him; <hi>Heaping to your ſelves Teachers, having Itching Ears,</hi> as it was Propheſy'd of theſe moſt degenerate Times, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> iv. 3.</p>
               <p>But as to thoſe well-diſpos'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> for whoſe Information Chiefly I have wrote this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> I muſt ſuppoſe that their Inquiry is wholly concerning the ſeveral <hi>Titles</hi> of <hi>Biſhops, Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, Independents,</hi> &amp;c. to the true <hi>Succeſſion</hi> from the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles:</hi> That it may <hi>thereby</hi> be known, to which of all theſe they ought to go for <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I have ſhewn, in behalf of <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> and put the <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> to prove their <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> in the Form of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> which they can never do: Becauſe, as I have ſaid before, the <hi>Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> does not Compute from the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41791:10"/>
                  <hi>Presbyters,</hi> but only of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as being the <hi>Chief Governors</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> And therefore, tho' in many <hi>Biſhopricks,</hi> the <hi>Roll</hi> of their <hi>Biſhops</hi> is preſerv'd from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> to this Day; yet there is not one bare <hi>Presbyter,</hi> that is, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of a <hi>Pariſh,</hi> and no more, no not in all the World, who can give a <hi>Roll</hi> of his <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> in that <hi>Pariſh,</hi> half way to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> or near it: For, from the firſt Plantation of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> was Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into <hi>Biſhopricks;</hi> this was neceſſary for the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church:</hi> But it was not ſo early Sub-divided into <hi>Pariſhes.</hi> The <hi>Presbyters,</hi> at firſt, attending upon the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> were ſent out by him, to ſuch <hi>Places,</hi> and for ſuch <hi>Time</hi> as he thought fit; and Returning, gave Account of their <hi>Stewardſhips,</hi> or were <hi>Viſited,</hi> and <hi>Changed</hi> by him, as he ſaw Cauſe: And therefore, tho' one might come after another, in the Place where he had <hi>Miniſtred</hi> before; yet they cou'd not <hi>Properly</hi> be ſaid to <hi>Succeed</hi> one another; as (to ſpeak Intelligibly to the <hi>Quakers</hi>) many of them do Preach after <hi>G. Fox,</hi> yet none of them are ſaid to <hi>Succeed</hi> him.</p>
               <p>I have been thus long upon the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> becauſe they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of all our <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> have any <hi>Pretence</hi> to <hi>Succeſſion.</hi> And what I have ſaid, as to them, muſt Operate more ſtrongly againſt the later <hi>Independent, Baptiſt, &amp;c.</hi> who have not the Face to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> but ſet up merely upon their own pretended <hi>Gifts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">VIII. But what are theſe <hi>Gifts,</hi> which they ſo Highly <hi>Boaſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. An <hi>Inward,</hi> and more than <hi>Ordinary</hi> Participation of the <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of the Holy <hi>Spirit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. A <hi>Fluency</hi> and <hi>Powerfulneſs</hi> in <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Praying.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>I know of no other <hi>Gifts</hi> that any of our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> pretend to, unleſs they will ſet up for <hi>Miracles,</hi> as <hi>G. Fox,</hi> &amp;c. And other <hi>Diſſenters</hi> did likewiſe pretend to the ſame, at their firſt ſetting out, to amuſe the People; but (as the <hi>Quakers</hi>) have let it drop after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to ſtop any further Examination of it; having already ſerv'd their Turn by it.</p>
               <p>But, as to theſe pretended <hi>Gifts,</hi> if we may truſt to our <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi>'s Rule, of knowing the <hi>Tree</hi> by its <hi>Fruits,</hi> we cannot think it the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of which theſe Men did partake, who fill'd theſe <hi>three Nations</hi> with <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Slaughter;</hi> and whoſe <hi>Religion</hi> was never otherwiſe Introduc'd, than by <hi>Rebellion,</hi> in any Country whither-ſoever it has yet come.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41791:11"/>
               <p>And as to that <hi>Volubility</hi> of <hi>Tongue,</hi> which they Boaſt, as the main <hi>Proof</hi> of their <hi>Miſſion,</hi> we have found it by Experience, that a little <hi>Confidence</hi> and <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> will Improve very ſlender <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> to great <hi>Readineſs</hi> in that ſort of <hi>Talent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>Powerfulneſs</hi> which is found in it by ſome, who are affected with a Diſmal <hi>Tone,</hi> Wray <hi>Faces,</hi> and Antick <hi>Geſtures,</hi> is not <hi>more</hi> but <hi>leſs,</hi> if there be either <hi>Method</hi> or <hi>Senſe</hi> in the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe:</hi> Which ſhews their <hi>Paſſion</hi> to proceed not from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but <hi>Imagination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Scots Presbyterian-Eloquence</hi> affords us <hi>Monſtrous</hi> Proofs of this; but not ſo many, as you may have from <hi>Eye</hi> and <hi>Ear-Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such <hi>Courſe, Rude,</hi> and <hi>Naſty</hi> Treatment of <hi>God,</hi> as they call <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion;</hi> as in it ſelf, it is the higheſt <hi>Affront</hi> to The <hi>Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty;</hi> ſo has it Contributed, in a very great Meaſure, to that wild <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> which has always attended theſe ſort of <hi>Inſpirations:</hi> It ſeeming to many, more Reaſonable to Worſhip no <hi>God</hi> at all, than to ſet up one, on purpoſe to <hi>Ridicule</hi> Him.</p>
               <p>But this ſort of <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> preſumes upon a <hi>Familiarity</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> which breeds <hi>Contempt,</hi> and Deſpiſes the <hi>Sobriety</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> as a low Diſpenſation. I Recommend to the Reader that Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Sermon,</hi> upon this Subject, of Dr. <hi>Hicks,</hi> call'd <hi>The Spirit of Enthuſiaſm Exorcis'd.</hi> And I deſire thoſe to conſider, who are moſt taken with theſe ſeeming Extraordinary Gifts of <hi>Volubility</hi> and <hi>Nimbleneſs</hi> in <hi>Prayer,</hi> that the moſt <hi>Wicked</hi> Men are capable of this Perfection; none more than <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> eſpecially when he was about ſome <hi>Nefarious Wickedneſs:</hi> He continu'd moſt <hi>Fluently</hi> in this <hi>Exerciſe,</hi> all the time that his <hi>Cut-throats</hi> were <hi>Murthering</hi> of his <hi>Royal Maſter.</hi> And his <hi>Gift</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Admir'd. <hi>Major weir</hi> of <hi>Edinborough,</hi> was another great Inſtance, who was ſtrangely Ador'd for his <hi>Gifts,</hi> eſpecially of <hi>Prayer,</hi> by the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in <hi>Scotland;</hi> while, at the ſame time, he was wallowing in the moſt <hi>Unnatural</hi> and <hi>Monſtrous</hi> Sins. See his Stupendous Story in <hi>Ravillac Redivivus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are many Examples of this Nature, which ſhew that this <hi>Gift</hi> is attainable by <hi>Art.</hi> Dr. <hi>wilkins</hi> (the Father of the <hi>Latitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarians</hi>) has given us the <hi>Receipt,</hi> in his <hi>Gift of Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet none of the Performances of theſe <hi>Gifted-men</hi> are any ways Comparable (as to the wonderful <hi>Readineſs</hi> in which they Boaſt)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41791:11"/>to the <hi>Extempore Verſes</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter School,</hi> which <hi>Iſaac Voſſius</hi> cou'd not believe to be <hi>Extempore,</hi> till he gave the <hi>Boys</hi> a <hi>Theme,</hi> which was <hi>ſenes bis Pueri,</hi> and he had no ſooner ſpoke the Words, but he was immediately Pelted with Ingenious <hi>Epigrams</hi> from four or five Boys.</p>
               <p>So that this <hi>Volubility</hi> in <hi>Prayer,</hi> which is the <hi>Gift</hi> our <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> do moſt Glory in, may be deduc'd from an <hi>Original</hi> far ſhort of <hi>Divine Inſpiration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe that they had really thoſe wonderful <hi>Gifts</hi> which they pretend to, yet were this no ground at all to Countenance or Warrant their makeing a <hi>Schiſm,</hi> upon that Account.</p>
               <p>This Caſe has been Rul'd in a Famous and moſt Remarkable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it, which God was pleas'd to permit, (for the future In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of His Church) at the firſt ſetting out of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> in the very Days of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then it was that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> having <hi>Aſcended up on High,</hi> gave many and <hi>miraculous Giſts</hi> unto Men; which was neceſſary towards the firſt Propagation of His <hi>Goſpel,</hi> in Oppoſition to all the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Religions</hi> and <hi>Governments</hi> then in the World, and under their <hi>Perſecution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe <hi>Gifts</hi> of <hi>Miracles</hi> did not always ſecure the <hi>Poſſeſſors</hi> from <hi>Vanity,</hi> and an high Opinion of themſelves, to the diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of others; and even to break the <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> by advancing themſelves above their <hi>Superiors;</hi> or think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none <hi>Superior</hi> to themſelves.</p>
               <p>The Great <hi>Apoſtle</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> was not free'd from the <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of this; whom the <hi>Meſſenger of Satan was ſent to buffet, leaſt he ſhou'd be Exalted above meaſure, thro' the Abundance of the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which were given to him,</hi> 2 Cor. xii. 7. Nay more, our Bleſſed <hi>Saviour</hi> tells of thoſe who had <hi>miraculous Gifts</hi> beſtow'd upon them, and yet ſhou'd be finally <hi>Rejected,</hi> Matth. vii. 22, 23. Therefore He Inſtructs His Diſciples not to Rejoyce in thoſe <hi>Miraculous Gifts</hi> which he beſtow'd upon them, but rather <hi>that their Names were written in Heaven, Luke</hi> x. 20. which ſuppoſes, that they might have ſuch <hi>Gifts,</hi> and yet their <hi>Names</hi> not be written in <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And when He taught them how to <hi>Pray,</hi> He added no Petition for ſuch <hi>Gifts,</hi> but only for the Remiſſion of their <hi>Sins,</hi> and the <hi>Sanctifying Graces</hi> of the Holy <hi>Spirit;</hi> which are, as moſt <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to <hi>Us,</hi> ſo moſt <hi>Precious</hi> in the ſight of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:41791:12"/>
               <p>Now ſome who had theſe <hi>Miraculous Gifts</hi> made ill uſe of them, and occaſion'd a great <hi>Schiſm</hi> (the firſt in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church) at <hi>Corinth.</hi> They were <hi>Exalted</hi> above <hi>Meaſure,</hi> in their own <hi>Gifts;</hi> and therefore Refus'd to ſubmit themſelves to thoſe who were their <hi>Superiors</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> (who, perhaps, had not ſuch <hi>Gifts</hi> as they had) but ſet up for themſelves, and drew Parties after them, who were Charm'd with their <hi>Extraordinary Gifts;</hi> thinking that the Participation of the <hi>ſaving Graces</hi> of the Holy <hi>Spirit</hi> muſt there Chiefly be Communicated, where God had beſtow'd ſuch <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Gifts.</hi> And they laid more ſtreſs upon the <hi>Perſonal Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> of theſe <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> than upon the obſervance of that <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> which He had Commanded; which was, in Effect, preferring <hi>Men</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and truſting to the <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> rather than to the <hi>Author</hi> of their <hi>Religion;</hi> as if thro' the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrators</hi> of God's <hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> and not from <hi>Him</hi> alone, the <hi>Graces</hi> which were Promis'd to the due Obſervance of them, were convey'd. <hi>Act.</hi> iii. 12.</p>
               <p>And this, as it turn'd Men from <hi>God,</hi> to Truſt in <hi>Man,</hi> ſo, as a neceſſary Conſequence of it, it begot great <hi>Emulations</hi> among the People for one <hi>Teacher</hi> againſt another, even (ſometimes) when it was not the Fault of the <hi>Teachers.</hi> For People being once let looſe from <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> to follow the <hi>Imaginations</hi> of their own <hi>Brain,</hi> will run farther than their firſt <hi>Seducers</hi> did Intend; and will Carve for themſelves.</p>
               <p>Thus, in the <hi>Schiſm</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> at <hi>Corinth,</hi> one was for <hi>Paul,</hi> another for <hi>Apollos,</hi> another for <hi>Cephas,</hi> &amp;c. much againſt the Minds of theſe good <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> but having been once unſettl'd by the <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Ambition</hi> of <hi>Seducers,</hi> they <hi>Heaped to themſelves Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, having itching Ears;</hi> and made <hi>Diviſions</hi> among themſelves, Pretendingly in behalf of <hi>Christ</hi> and His <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> but in Effect, tending to Divide <hi>Chriſt</hi> and His <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as all <hi>Schiſms</hi> do.</p>
               <p>Againſt theſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> Diſputes with wonderful force of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Eloquence;</hi> particularly in the xii <hi>Chap.</hi> of his firſt <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to theſe ſame <hi>Corinthians;</hi> wherein, from the Parallel of the <hi>Unity</hi> of <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> in the ſame <hi>Body,</hi> he admirably Illuſtrates, That the many Different and <hi>Miraculous Gifts</hi> which were then Diſpenſed all from the ſame <hi>Spirit,</hi> cou'd be no more an Argumeut for any to Advance himſelf beyond his own Station in the <hi>Church,</hi> than for one <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> tho' an <hi>Eye</hi> or a <hi>Hand,</hi> the moſt <hi>Uſeful</hi> or <hi>Beautiful,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:41791:12"/>to Glory it ſelf againſt the <hi>Inferior Members</hi> (who are all Actuated by the ſame <hi>Soul</hi>) or not to be Content with its <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Station</hi> in the <hi>Body,</hi> and due <hi>Subordination</hi> to the <hi>Head.</hi> Thence the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> goes on, and makes the Application in the xiiith. <hi>Chap.</hi> That the moſt Exalted <hi>Spiritual</hi> or even <hi>Miraculous Gifts</hi> cou'd not only not Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe any <hi>Schiſm</hi> to be made in the <hi>Body,</hi> that is, the <hi>Church;</hi> But that if any who had ſuch <hi>Gifts,</hi> did not employ them for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the <hi>Unity</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> which is very properly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd by <hi>Charity,</hi> i.e. <hi>Love</hi> for the whole <hi>Body,</hi> ſuch <hi>Gifts</hi> wou'd <hi>Profit</hi> him <hi>Nothing,</hi> looſe all their <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Efficacy,</hi> as to the <hi>Poſſeſſor,</hi> and be rather an <hi>Aggravation</hi> againſt him, than any <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe</hi> for him, to withdraw his Obedience from his lawful <hi>Superiors,</hi> and Uſurp the Office of the <hi>Head;</hi> and ſo make a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the <hi>Body,</hi> upon the account of his <hi>Gifts;</hi> which tho' they were as great as to ſpeak with the <hi>Tongues</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> to underſtand all <hi>Myſteries,</hi> and all <hi>Knowledge;</hi> to have all <hi>Faith,</hi> even to Remove <hi>Mountains;</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Zeal</hi> as to give all his <hi>Goods</hi> to the <hi>Poor,</hi> and his very <hi>Body</hi> to be <hi>Burned,</hi> yet, if it be done in <hi>Schiſm,</hi> out of that <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> which is due to the <hi>Body,</hi> and to its <hi>Unity,</hi> all is <hi>Nothing,</hi> will profit him nothing at all.</p>
               <p>And no wonder, when all that <hi>Heavenly Glory</hi> in which <hi>Lucifer</hi> was Created, cou'd avail him nothing,
<note place="margin">Jude 6.</note> when he <hi>kept not his firſt Principality,</hi> but Aſpir'd <hi>Higher,</hi> and made a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How then ſhall they who have (as St. <hi>Jude</hi> expreſſes it) <hi>left their own Habitation,</hi> or <hi>Station</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and advanc'd themſelves above their <hi>Biſhops,</hi> their lawful <hi>Superiors,</hi> the <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of <hi>Unity,</hi> next and immediately under <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in their Reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <hi>Churches,</hi> upon pretence of their own Perſonal <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications,</hi> and thereby make a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the <hi>Terreſtrial Hierarchy</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> which is the <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.23.</note> the <hi>Fulneſs of him who Filleth all in all:</hi> How ſhall they be Excus'd for this, whoſe pretended <hi>Gifts</hi> are in nothing <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> except in a <hi>Furious Zeal</hi> without <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and a <hi>Volubility</hi> of <hi>Tongue,</hi> which proceeds from a Habit of <hi>Speaking</hi> without <hi>Thinking;</hi> and an <hi>Aſſurance</hi> that is never out of <hi>Countenance</hi> for Ten Thouſand <hi>Blunders,</hi> which wou'd <hi>Daſh</hi> and <hi>Confound</hi> any Man of <hi>Senſe</hi> or <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty,</hi> or that conſider'd the <hi>Preſence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> in which he ſpoke?</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:41791:13"/>
               <p>If thoſe truly <hi>Miraculous Gifts,</hi> which were made a Pretence for the <hi>Schiſm</hi> at <hi>Corinth,</hi> were not ſufficient to juſtifie that <hi>Schiſm:</hi> How <hi>Ridiculous</hi> and much more <hi>wicked</hi> is the <hi>Pretence</hi> of our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Gifted-men,</hi> who have pleaded their Delicate <hi>Gifts</hi> as a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Ground for all that <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> which they have Rais'd up amongſt us?</p>
               <p>If the real <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Inſpirations</hi> of the Holy <hi>Spirit</hi> were <hi>Stinted</hi> and <hi>Limited</hi> by the <hi>Governors</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> to avaid <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> in the <hi>Church:</hi> If the <hi>Prophets</hi> were <hi>Confin'd</hi> as to their <hi>Number,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. xiv. <hi>from</hi> v. 26.</note> to <hi>Two,</hi> or at the moſt <hi>Three</hi> at a time; ſome ordered to <hi>hold their Peace,</hi> to give place to others; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to <hi>keep ſilence</hi> for want of an <hi>Interpreter;</hi> and the <hi>Women</hi> (tho' <hi>Gifted</hi> or <hi>Inſpir'd</hi> as many then were) totally <hi>ſilenc'd</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 11.12.</note> or <hi>Publick Aſſemblies:</hi> What <hi>Spirit</hi> has Poſſeſs'd our <hi>Modern Pretenders</hi> to <hi>Gifts,</hi> that will not be ſubject to the <hi>Prophets,</hi> nor to the <hi>Church,</hi> nor to any <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> whether <hi>Divine</hi> or <hi>Humane!</hi> But if their <hi>Superiors</hi> pretend to <hi>Direct</hi> them in any thing, they cry out, what! will you <hi>ſtint</hi> the <hi>Spirit!</hi> And think this a ſufficient Cauſe to break quite looſe from their <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and ſet up an open <hi>Schiſm</hi> againſt them, upon Pretence of their wonderful <hi>Gifts</hi> forſooth!</p>
               <p>That firſt <hi>Schiſm</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> was vigorouſly oppos'd by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> at that time. They, like good <hi>Watch-men,</hi> wou'd not give way to it, knowing the fatal Conſequences of it.</p>
               <p>This produc'd <hi>Two Epiſtles</hi> from St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and <hi>Two</hi> to them from St. <hi>Clement,</hi> then <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, and handed down to us. It was this ſame occaſion of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which ſo early began to Corrupt the <hi>Church,</hi> that led the Holy <hi>Ignatius</hi> (who flouriſh'd in that ſame Age) to preſs ſo Earneſtly in all his <hi>Epiſtles</hi> to the ſeveral <hi>Churches</hi> to whom he wrote, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſable obligation of a ſtrict <hi>Obedience</hi> to their Reſpective <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</hi> That the <hi>Laity</hi> ſhou'd ſubmit themſelves to the <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> as to the <hi>Apoſtolical College</hi> under <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and that the <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi> as well as the <hi>Laity,</hi> ſhou'd <hi>Obey</hi> their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> Himſelf; whoſe Perſon he did Repreſent: That therefore whoever kept not <hi>Outward Communion</hi> with his <hi>Biſhop,</hi> did forfeit his <hi>Inward Communion</hi> with <hi>Chriſt:</hi> That no <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> were <hi>Valid,</hi> or <hi>Acceptable</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> which were not cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41791:13"/>in Communion with the <hi>Biſhop.</hi> That nothing in the <hi>Church</hi> ſhou'd be done, nor any <hi>Marriage</hi> Contracted without the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s Conſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As you will ſee hereafter.</p>
               <p>Theſe clear Teſtimonies fore'd the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> (becauſe they were not in a Temper to be Convinc'd) to deny theſe <hi>Epiſtles</hi> of St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> to be Genuine. But they have been ſo fully Vindicated, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by the moſt Learned Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> Dr. <hi>Pearſon,</hi> as to ſilence that Cavil, and leave no Pretence remaining againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in that <hi>Primitive</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Age.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>Objection from the Times of</hi> Popery <hi>in this Kingdom; as if that did</hi> Un-Church, <hi>and conſequently break the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our</hi> Biſhops.</head>
               <p>I muſt now Account for an Objection, which with ſome, ſeems a mighty one, even enough to overthrow all that I have ſaid concerning the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of our <hi>Biſhops:</hi> And that is, the long <hi>Mid-night</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> which has, in old Time, Darken'd theſe Nations.</p>
               <p>Well. The <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> of which I have been ſpeaking, was no Part of that Darkneſs; and we have, by God's Bleſſing, recover'd our ſelves, in a great Meaſure, from that Darkneſs. But that Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was ſuch, as, with ſome, to Deſtroy the <hi>Epiſcopal Succeſſion;</hi> becauſe, as they ſay, ſuch <hi>great Errors,</hi> eſpecially that of <hi>Idolatry,</hi> does quite <hi>Un-church</hi> a People; and conſequently muſt break their <hi>Succeſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">I. This, by the way, is a <hi>Popiſh</hi> Argument, tho' they that now make it, are not a ware of it. For the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> argues thus, That <hi>Idolatry</hi> does <hi>Un-church;</hi> and therefore, if ſhe was <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous,</hi> for ſo long a time as we charge upon her, it will follow that, for ſo many Ages, there was no <hi>Viſible Church,</hi> at leaſt, in theſe <hi>Weſtern</hi> Parts of the World. And <hi>Arianiſm</hi> (which is <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi>) having broke in ſeveral times upon the <hi>Church;</hi> if <hi>Idolatry</hi> did quite <hi>Un-church;</hi> and Break the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> ther wou'd not be a <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> hardly left in the World. The Conſequence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41791:14"/>of which wou'd be as fatal to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> as to us: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let her look to that Poſition, which ſhe has advanced againſt us, that <hi>Idolatry</hi> does <hi>Un-church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. But that it does not <hi>Un-church,</hi> I have this to offer againſt thoſe <hi>Papiſts, Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Others</hi> who make the Objection.</p>
               <p n="1">I. If it does quite <hi>Un-church,</hi> then cou'd no <hi>Chriſtian</hi> be an <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> becauſe, by that, he wou'd, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> ceaſe to be a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the <hi>Chriſtian Church:</hi> But the <hi>Scripture</hi> does ſuppoſe that a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> may be an <hi>Idolater:</hi> Therefore <hi>Idolatry</hi> does not <hi>Un-church.</hi> The <hi>Minor</hi> is prov'd, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> v. 11. <hi>If any Man that is called a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (that is, a <hi>Chriſtian</hi>) <hi>be a Fornicator, or Covetous, or an Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>—Nay, <hi>Eph.</hi> v. 5. <hi>a covetous man</hi> is call'd an <hi>Idolater;</hi> and <hi>Col.</hi> iii. 5. <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> is <hi>Idolatry.</hi> So that, by this Argument, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs</hi> does <hi>Un-church.</hi> If it be ſaid, that <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> is call'd <hi>Idolatry,</hi> only by Alluſion, but that it is not <hi>Formal</hi> Idolatry: I know no Ground for that Diſtinction. The <hi>Scripture</hi> calls it <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> and makes no Diſtinction. But,</p>
               <p n="2">2dly, In the firſt Text quoted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> v. 11. both <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> are Nam'd; ſo that, you have both <hi>Material</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal,</hi> or what other ſort of <hi>Idolatry</hi> you pleaſe to fanſie.</p>
               <p>I grant, that, in one ſenſe, <hi>Idolatry</hi> does <hi>Un-church;</hi> that is, while we continue in it, it renders us Obnoxious to the <hi>Wrath</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and forfeits our Title to the <hi>Promiſes</hi> which are made to the <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> But, ſo does <hi>Fornication, Covetouſneſs,</hi> and every other <hi>Sin,</hi> till we <hi>Repent,</hi> and <hi>Return</hi> from it. But none of theſe Sins do ſo <hi>Un-church</hi> us, as to Exclude our Returning to the <hi>Fold,</hi> by ſincere Repentance; or to need a ſecond <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> or <hi>Admiſſion</hi> into the <hi>Church:</hi> Neither does <hi>Idolatry.</hi> Do I then put <hi>Idolatry</hi> upon the level with other common Sins? No, far from it. Every <hi>Scab</hi> is not a <hi>Leproſie;</hi> yet a <hi>Leper</hi> is a <hi>Man,</hi> and may Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his Health. <hi>Idolatry</hi> is a fearful <hi>Leproſie;</hi> but it does not therefore quite <hi>Un-church,</hi> nor throw us out of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> For, if it did, then wou'd not <hi>Repentance</hi> heal it; becauſe <hi>Repentance</hi> is a great Part of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> And therefore, ſince none deny <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> to an <hi>Idolater;</hi> it follows that he is not yet quite out of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> Some of the Ancients have deny'd Repentance to <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> yet granted it to <hi>Idolatry;</hi> which ſhews that they did not look upon <hi>Idolatry</hi> to be an abſolute <hi>Apoſtacy;</hi> for every <hi>Sin</hi> is an <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> in a Limited ſenſe.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41791:14"/>
               <p n="2">2. Let us, in this Diſquiſition, follow the Example before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd, of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>moſt Primitive Fathers,</hi> to meaſure the <hi>Chriſtian Church</hi> with its exact <hi>Type,</hi> the Church under the <hi>Law;</hi> which are not <hi>Two Churches,</hi> but Two <hi>States</hi> of the ſame <hi>Church,</hi> for it is the ſame <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church, from the firſt Promiſe of <hi>Chriſt, Gen.</hi> iii. 15. to the End of the World. And therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> iv. 2. That the <hi>Goſpel</hi> was Preached unto <hi>Them,</hi> as well as unto <hi>Us.</hi> And theſe two <hi>States</hi> of the Church, <hi>before</hi> and <hi>after</hi> Chriſt, do Anſwer, like a pair of <hi>Indentures</hi> to one another; the one being, to an <hi>Iota</hi> fulfilled in the other.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> v. 18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now we find frequent Lapſes to <hi>Idolatry</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jews:</hi> Yet did not this <hi>Un-church</hi> them; no, nor deprive them of a competent meaſure of God's Holy Spirit; as it is written, <hi>Neh.</hi> ix. 18, 20. <hi>Yea, when they had made them a molten calf, and ſaid, this is thy God—yet thou, in thy manifold Mercies, forſookeſt them not —Thou gaveſt thy good ſpirit to inſtruct them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And let it be here obſerv'd, That tho' God ſent many <hi>Prophets</hi> to Reprove the great <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> as well of their <hi>Prieſts</hi> as <hi>People;</hi> yet none of theſe <hi>Holy Prophets</hi> did ſeparate Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the <hi>Wicked Prieſts:</hi> They wou'd not joyn in their <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Worſhip; but in all other Parts, they joyn'd with them; and ſet up no oppoſit <hi>Prieſthood</hi> to them. So little did the <hi>Prophets</hi> think that their <hi>Idolatry</hi> had either <hi>Un-church'd</hi> them, or broke the <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> of their <hi>Prieſts;</hi> or that it was Lawful for any, how <hi>Holy</hi> ſoever, to uſurp upon their <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> and ſupply the Deficiencies of it to the <hi>People.</hi> And apply to this, what I have before ſhewn, in the words of St. <hi>Clement, whoſe Name is written in the Book of Life,</hi> That the <hi>Evangelical Prieſthood,</hi> is as ſurely fixed; in the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and its <hi>Succeſſion</hi> continu'd in thoſe <hi>Ordain'd</hi> by them, as the <hi>Levitical Prieſthood</hi> was confirm'd by the Budding of <hi>Aaron</hi>'s <hi>Rod,</hi> and to be continu'd in that <hi>Tribe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">III. And here let our <hi>Korahites,</hi> of ſeveral ſizes, take a view of the Heinouſneſs of their <hi>Schiſm;</hi> and let them not think their Crime to be nothing, becauſe they have been taught, with their Nurſes Milk, to have the utmoſt abhorrence to the very Name of a <hi>Biſhop;</hi> tho' they cou'd not tell why. Let them rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſeriouſly the misfortune of their Education, which ſhou'd make them Strangers, to all the reſt of the Chriſtian World but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:41791:15"/>themſelves in a Corner; and to all the former Ages of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They have been told that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is <hi>Popery;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> have <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So have they <hi>Presbyters</hi> too, that is, <hi>Pariſh Prieſts:</hi> They have the <hi>Creed</hi> likewiſe, and the Holy <hi>Scriptures;</hi> and all theſe muſt be <hi>Popiſh,</hi> if this be a good <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, are they willing to be undeceived? Then they muſt know that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> has none ſo great an Enemy as the <hi>Papacy;</hi> which wou'd Engroſs the whole <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Power, into the ſingle <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> by making all other <hi>Biſhops</hi> abſolutly dependent upon that, which only they call the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Chair. And no longer ſince than the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent,</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> endeavor'd, with all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to have <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> except only that of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be declar'd not to be <hi>Jure Divino.</hi> By which no other <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> cou'd claim any other Power, but what they had from Him. But that <hi>Council</hi> was not ſo quite Degenerated as to ſuffer this to paſs.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and Others, who Diſputed there on the <hi>Pope</hi>'s part, us'd thoſe ſame Arguments againſt the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> which from them, and the <hi>Popiſh Canoniſts</hi> and <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> have been lick'd up by the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and others of our <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> They are the ſame Arguments which are us'd by <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When the <hi>Pope</hi> cou'd not carry his Cauſe againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> he took another Method, and that was, to ſet up a vaſt Number of <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Prieſts, that is, the <hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,</hi> whom he Exempted from the <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> of their reſpective <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and fram'd them into a <hi>Method</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of their own, accountable only to <hi>Superiors</hi> of his, and their own contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving; which is exactly the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Model.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Uſurpations</hi> upon the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Authority, made the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> quit his great Preferments in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Travel into <hi>England,</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> I. to ſeek for a more <hi>Primitive</hi> and <hi>Independent Epiſcopacy.</hi> Himſelf, in his <hi>Conſilium Profectionis,</hi> gives theſe ſame Reaſons for it: And that this ſhameful <hi>Depreſſion</hi> and <hi>Proſtitution</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the cauſe of his leaving her.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:41791:15"/>
               <p>He obſerv'd truly, that the further we ſearch upward in <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> there is ſtill more to be found of the <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> and leſs of the <hi>Papal</hi> Eminency.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> is full, in every line almoſt, of the high Authority of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> next and immediately under <hi>Chriſt;</hi> as all the other Writers in thoſe Primitive Times: But there is a profound ſilence in them all of that <hi>Supremacy</hi> in the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is now claim'd over all the other <hi>Biſhops</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church:</hi> Which cou'd not be, if it had been then known in the World. This had been a ſhort and effectual Method, whereby St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or St. <hi>Clement</hi> might have quieted the great <hi>Schiſm</hi> of the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> againſt which they both wrote, in their <hi>Epiſtles</hi> to them; to bid them refer their Differences to the <hi>Infallible Judge</hi> of <hi>Contre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy,</hi> the <hi>Supreme Paſtor</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> But not a word like this. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was one, for whom ſome of theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> ſtrove (1 Cor. i. 12.) againſt thoſe who preferred others before Him.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Uſurp'd Supremacy</hi> of the later <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> over their <hi>Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Biſhops,</hi> has been as Fatal to <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as the Rebellion of our yet later <hi>Presbyters</hi> againſt their Reſpective <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed, whoever wou'd write the true Hiſtory of <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianiſm,</hi> muſt begin at <hi>Rome,</hi> and not at <hi>Geneva.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So very <hi>Groundleſs,</hi> as well as <hi>Malicious,</hi> is that popular Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> having any Relation to <hi>Popery.</hi> They are ſo utterly Irreconcilable, that it is impoſſible they can ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For that moment that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> were Reſtor'd to its Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Independency, the <hi>Papacy,</hi> that is, that <hi>Supremacy,</hi> which does now diſtinguiſh it, muſt <hi>ipſo facto</hi> ceaſe. But enough of this, for I muſt not digreſs into various Subjects.</p>
               <p>I have ſhewn, in Anſwer to the Objection of the Ages of <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> in this Kingdom, that all thoſe <hi>Errors,</hi> even <hi>Idolatry</hi> it ſelf, does not <hi>Un-church,</hi> nor break <hi>Succeſſion.</hi> And <hi>2dly,</hi> I have Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifi'd this from the Parallel of the <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> under the <hi>Law.</hi> Then applying of this to our Caſe, I have vindicared <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> from the Imputation of <hi>Popery.</hi> I will now go on to further <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> why the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of our preſent <hi>Biſhops</hi> is not hurt by that Deluge of <hi>Popery,</hi> which once cover'd the face of this Land.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. The end of all <hi>Government,</hi> as well in the <hi>Church</hi> as <hi>State,</hi> is to preſerve <hi>Peace, Unity,</hi> and <hi>Order;</hi> and this cannot be done,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:41791:16"/>if the <hi>Male-adminiſtration</hi> of the <hi>Officers</hi> in the Government, did <hi>Vacat.</hi> their <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> without its being Re-call'd by thoſe who gave ſuch <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to them. For then, 1ſt. Every Man muſt be Judge, when ſuch a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> is <hi>Vacated;</hi> and then no Man is bound to obey longer then he pleaſes. 2dly, One may ſay it is <hi>Vacated,</hi> another not; whence perpetual Contention muſt ariſe.</p>
               <p>A Man may <hi>Forfeit</hi> his Commiſſion, that is, do thoſe things, which give juſt Cauſe to his <hi>Superiors</hi> to take it from him: But it is not actually <hi>Vacated,</hi> till it be actually <hi>Recall'd</hi> by thoſe who have lawful Power to take it from him: Otherwiſe their cou'd be no <hi>Peace</hi> nor <hi>Certainty</hi> in the World, either in <hi>Publick</hi> or in <hi>Private</hi> affairs. No <hi>Family</hi> cou'd ſubſiſt. No Man enjoy an <hi>Eſtate.</hi> No <hi>Society</hi> whatever cou'd keep together: And the <hi>Church</hi> being an <hi>Outward Society</hi> (as ſhewn in the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> of <hi>Water Baptiſm</hi>) muſt conſequently ſubſiſt by thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> which are indiſpenſible to every <hi>Society.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sect. iii.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1.</note> And tho' <hi>Idolatry</hi> does juſtly <hi>Forfeit</hi> the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> of any <hi>Church,</hi> in this ſenſe, that God's Promiſes to Her being <hi>Conditional,</hi> He may juſtly take her <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> from her, and <hi>Remove</hi> her <hi>Candleſtick:</hi> Now tho' her <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> be thus <hi>Forfeitable,</hi> yet it ſtill <hi>Continues,</hi> and is not actually <hi>Pacated,</hi> till God ſhall pleaſe <hi>actually</hi> to Recall it, or take it away: For no <hi>Commiſſion</hi> is <hi>Void,</hi> till it be ſo <hi>Declar'd.</hi> Thus, tho' the <hi>Jews</hi> did often fall into <hi>Idolatry,</hi> yet (as before has been ſaid) God did bear long with them; and did not <hi>Un-church</hi> them, tho' they had juſtly <hi>Forfeited.</hi> And theſe wicked <hi>Husband men,</hi> who ſlew thoſe whom the <hi>Lord</hi> ſent for the Fruits of His <hi>Vineyard,</hi> yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd ſtill to be the <hi>Husband-men</hi> of the <hi>Vineyard,</hi> till their <hi>Lord</hi> did Diſpoſſeſs them, and gave their <hi>Vineyard</hi> unto others.</p>
               <p>And <hi>natural Reaſon</hi> does enforce this: If a <hi>Steward</hi> abuſe his Truſt, and oppreſſes the <hi>Tenants,</hi> yet are they ſtill oblig'd to pay their <hi>Rent</hi> to him, and his <hi>Diſcharges</hi> are ſufficient to them againſt their <hi>Landlord,</hi> till he ſhall <hi>Superſede</hi> ſuch a <hi>Steward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If a <hi>Captain</hi> wrong and cheat his <hi>Soldiers,</hi> yet are they oblig'd to remain under his Command, till the <hi>King,</hi> who gave him his <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> or thoſe to whom he has Committed ſuch an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, ſhall <hi>Caſhier</hi> him.</p>
               <p>And thus it is in the <hi>Sacerdotal Commiſſion,</hi> Abuſes in it, do not take it away, till God, or thoſe to whom He has Committed ſuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:41791:16"/>an Authority, ſhall <hi>Suſpend, Deprive,</hi> or <hi>Degrade</hi> (as the <hi>Fact</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires) ſuch a <hi>Biſhop</hi> or a <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And there is this higher Conſideration in the <hi>Sacerdotal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> than in thoſe of Civil Societies; That it being immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately from <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>none</hi> (therefore) <hi>can take this Honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was</hi> Aaron; ſo can none take it — way, but he that is as <hi>Expreſly</hi> and <hi>Outwardly</hi> called thereunto, as <hi>Aaron</hi> was to be a <hi>Prieſt.</hi> For this wou'd be to <hi>Uſurp</hi> upon <hi>God</hi>'s immediate <hi>Prerogative,</hi> which is to Conſtitute His own <hi>Prieſts.</hi> Upon this Foundation I argue.</p>
               <p n="5">V. As the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> and the general Commands in <hi>Scripture,</hi> of <hi>Obedience</hi> to <hi>Government</hi> do require our Submiſſion to the Government in being, where there is no <hi>Competition</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Titles,</hi> or any that <hi>Claims</hi> a <hi>better Right</hi> than the <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor:</hi> So where a <hi>Church,</hi> once Eſtabliſh'd by <hi>God,</hi> tho' ſuffering many Interruptions, does continue, Her <hi>Governors</hi> ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd, where ther is no <hi>better Claim</hi> ſet up againſt them.</p>
               <p>This was the Reaſon why our <hi>Saviour</hi> and His <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſcruple, acknowledge the <hi>High-Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Sanbedrin</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> in their time; tho' from the days of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> ther had been great <hi>Irruptions,</hi> and <hi>Breaches</hi> in the due <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of their <hi>Prieſts:</hi> and before <hi>Chriſt</hi> came, and all His time, the <hi>Romans,</hi> as <hi>Conquerors,</hi> diſpos'd of the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> as they pleas'd; and made it <hi>Annual</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> had appointed <hi>Hereditary</hi> and <hi>Unmovable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ther was then no <hi>Competition:</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> did ſubmit to it, becauſe they were under the ſubjection of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and cou'd have no other. No <hi>High-Priest</hi> claimed againſt him in Poſſeſſion, but all ſubmitted to him.</p>
               <p>And our <hi>Saviour</hi> did confirm His Authority, and of the <hi>Sanhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drin,</hi> or Inferior <hi>Prieſts</hi> with him, (<hi>Matth.</hi> xxiii. 2.) <hi>ſaying, the Scribes and Phariſees ſit in Moſes's ſeat. All therefore, whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and de.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> own'd the Authority of the <hi>High-Prieſt, Act.</hi> xxiii. 5.</p>
               <p>Many Objections might have been rais'd againſt the Deduction of their <hi>Succeſſion</hi> from <hi>Moſes:</hi> But ther being none who claim'd any better Right than they had; therefore their <hi>Right</hi> was <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controverted;</hi> and by our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Authority was Confirm'd.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:41791:17"/>
               <p>Now ſuppoſe ſome <hi>Interruptions</hi> had been in the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> or <hi>Corruptions</hi> in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> of our <hi>Engliſh Biſhops,</hi> in former Ages, yet (as in the Caſe of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi>) that cou'd have no Effect to Invalidate their <hi>Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> at the preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>The</hi> Aſſurance <hi>and</hi> Conſent <hi>in the</hi> Epiſcopal <hi>Communion, beyond that of any other.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">I. THE whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, as it always has been, ſo at this Preſent, it is <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> except a few <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> who, in leſs than Two Hundred years laſt paſt, have ariſen, like a <hi>Wart</hi> upon the Face of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Church. For little more Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion do our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> here, the <hi>Hugonots</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> in <hi>Holland, Geneva,</hi> and thereabouts, bear to the whole Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the <hi>Latin</hi> Church, which is all <hi>Epiſcopal.</hi> But, if you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church all over the World, which is all <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> they will not appear ſo big as a <hi>Mole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">II. If our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> think it much, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhou'd be reckon'd in the Liſt againſt them; we will be content to leave them out: Nay more, if we ſhou'd give them all thoſe <hi>Churches,</hi> which own the <hi>Supremacy</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to be joyn'd with them (as they are the neareſt to them) it will be ſo far from caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Ballance on their ſide, that the other <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Churches will, by far, out-number them both.</p>
               <p>Let us then, to theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> againſt <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> add the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> of <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> entire, with the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Part of <hi>Germany, France, Poland</hi> and <hi>Hungary</hi> (I think they have no more to reckon upon,) againſt theſe we produce the vaſt <hi>Empire</hi> of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> (which is greater in Extent than all theſe <hi>Popiſh</hi> Countries before nam'd) <hi>England, Scotland, Denmark, Sweden,</hi> and all the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in <hi>Germany,</hi> which will out-number both the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> before-mention'd. And this compariſon is only made as to the <hi>Latin</hi> Church. But then, we have all the reſt of the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, wholly on the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> ſide, againſt both the <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41791:17"/>of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Parity</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterians.</hi> The whole <hi>Greek</hi> Church, the <hi>Armenians, Georgians, Mingrelians, Jacobites,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of St. <hi>Thomas,</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Oriental</hi> Churches. Then in <hi>Africa,</hi> the <hi>Cophties</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and great Empire of the <hi>Abyſſins</hi> in <hi>Aethiopia.</hi> Theſe all are <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal,</hi> and never own'd the <hi>Supremacy</hi> of <hi>Rome:</hi> And over reckon, out of ſight, all that diſown <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and all that own the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> with them.</p>
               <p n="3">III. Let me add, that among our <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> every Claſs of them does Condemn all the reſt; the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Damns the <hi>Quaker,</hi> the <hi>Quaker</hi> Damns him, <hi>Independent, Baptiſt,</hi> &amp;c. All Damn one another, and Each denys the others <hi>Ordination</hi> or <hi>Call.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that, the <hi>Ordination</hi> of every one of them, is diſown'd by all the reſt; and all of them together by the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World. And if their <hi>Ordinations</hi> are not Valid, then they have no more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to adminiſter the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> than any other <hi>Lay-men;</hi> and conſequently, ther can be no ſecurity in Receiving <hi>Baptiſm</hi> from any of them.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. What allowances God will make to thoſe who think their <hi>Ordination</hi> to be good enough, and that they are true <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and, as ſuch, do receive the <hi>Sacraments</hi> from them, I will not determine.</p>
               <p>But they have no reaſon to expect the like allowances who are warned of it before-hand, and will notwithſtanding venture upon it; before theſe <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>clearly</hi> acquit themſelves of ſo <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Univerſal</hi> a Charge laid againſt them; ſuch an one, as muſt make the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World <hi>wrong,</hi> if they be in the <hi>Right!</hi> Not only the preſent <hi>Chriſtian Churches,</hi> but all the Ages of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> ſince <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Of which the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd to produce any one, in any Part of the World, that were not <hi>Epiſcopal</hi>—any one Conſtituted <hi>Church</hi> upon the Face of the Earth, that was not Govern'd by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> diſtinct from, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to <hi>Presbyters,</hi> before the <hi>Vaudois</hi> in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> the <hi>Hugonots</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> in <hi>Geneva,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> thence Tranſplanted, in this laſt Age, into <hi>Holland, Scotland</hi> and <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. If it ſhou'd be retorted, that neither is the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> without <hi>Oppoſers;</hi> for, that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> oppoſes Her, as do likewiſe our <hi>Diſſenters.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41791:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> None of them do oppoſe Her, in the Point we are now upon, that is, the Validity of <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Ordination, which the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> does own; and the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> dare not deny it, becauſe they wou'd (thereby) overthrow all their own <hi>Ordinations;</hi> for the <hi>Presbyters</hi> who <hi>Reformed</hi> (as they call it) from <hi>Biſhops,</hi> receiv'd their <hi>Ordination</hi> from <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore, tho' the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Principles do <hi>Invalidate</hi> the <hi>Ordination</hi> by <hi>Presbyters,</hi> yet the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Principles do not <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validate</hi> the <hi>Ordination</hi> by <hi>Biſhops:</hi> So that the <hi>Validity</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopal Ordination</hi> ſtands ſafe, on all ſides, even by the Confeſſion of thoſe who are Enemies to the <hi>Epiſcopal Order:</hi> and, in this, the <hi>Biſhops</hi> have no oppoſers.</p>
               <p>Whereas, on the other hand, the <hi>Validity</hi> of the <hi>Presbyterian Ordinations,</hi> is own'd by none but themſelves; and they have all the reſt of the World as oppoſite to them.</p>
               <p>Therefore, to ſtate the Caſe the moſt Impartially; to receive <hi>Baptiſm</hi> from theſe <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> is, at leaſt, a <hi>hazard</hi> of many <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands</hi> to <hi>One;</hi> as many as all the reſt of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> are more than they: But to receive it from the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Clergy, has no <hi>hazard</hi> at all, as to its <hi>Validity,</hi> even as own'd by the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> themſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>The</hi> Perſonal Sanctity <hi>of the</hi> Adminiſtrator <hi>of the</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, <hi>tho' highly Requiſite on his Part, yet not of</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity <hi>as to the</hi> Receivers, <hi>to Convey to them the</hi> Benefits <hi>of the</hi> Sacraments.</head>
               <p n="1">I. THE only Objection of thoſe <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are otherwiſe convinc'd of the <hi>Obligation</hi> of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> is the <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity</hi> they think ther is of great <hi>Perſonal</hi> Holineſs in the <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrators;</hi> without which, they cannot ſee how the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the <hi>Sacraments</hi> can be convey'd. But I wou'd beſeech them to conſider, how, by this, inſtead of referring the Glory to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>leſſening</hi> the <hi>Performance</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> which I charitably
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41791:18"/>preſume (and I am confident as to ſome of whom I ſpeak) that it is their true and ſincere Intention; but inſtead of that, I do, in great Good will, invite them to reflect whither their well-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Zeal has turn'd the Point of this Queſtion—even to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-magnifie <hi>Man,</hi> and transfer the Glory of <hi>God</hi> unto His <hi>weak Inſtrument;</hi> as if any (the leaſt Part) of the <hi>Divine</hi> Vertue which God has annexed to His <hi>Sacraments</hi> did proceed from His <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> If this be not the meaning (as ſure it is not) why ſo much ſtreſs laid upon the <hi>Sanctity</hi> of the <hi>Miniſters?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. iii. 12.</note> as if thro' <hi>their power or holineſs</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> was given!</p>
               <p n="2">II. To obviate this pretence, our Saviour <hi>Chriſt</hi> choſe a <hi>Devil</hi> (<hi>John</hi> vi. 70.) to be one of His <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and he was ſent to <hi>Baptize</hi> and work <hi>Miracles</hi> as well as the reſt: And thoſe whom <hi>Judas</hi> did <hi>Baptize,</hi> were, no doubt, as well <hi>Baptized,</hi> and did partake of the Communication of the <hi>Spirit</hi> (according to their Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for it) as much as any who were <hi>Baptized</hi> by the other <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles;</hi> unleſs you will ſay that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſent him to <hi>Baptize,</hi> who had no Authority to <hi>Baptize,</hi> and that none ſhou'd receive Benefit by his <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which wou'd be to Cheat and Delude the People; and is a great Blaſphemy againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and a diſtruſt of His <hi>Power;</hi> as if it were <hi>Limited</hi> by the poor Inſtrument He pleaſes to make uſe off; whereas,</p>
               <p n="3">III. His <hi>Greatneſs</hi> is often moſt <hi>Magnify'd</hi> in the <hi>meaneſs</hi> of the <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> by which He works. Thus He deſtroy'd <hi>Egypt</hi> by <hi>Frogs</hi> and <hi>Lice;</hi> and the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> by <hi>Emerods</hi> and <hi>Mice;</hi> and ſent His <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>Flies</hi> and <hi>Hornets</hi> to diſpoſſeſs the <hi>Canaanites. Out of the mouths of babes and ſucklings haſt thou ordained ſtrength, becauſe of thine enemies,
<note place="margin">Pſal. viii. 2.</note> that thou mighteſt ſtill the enemy, and the avenger;</hi> i.e. That the Enemies of God might be confounded, when they ſaw His great Power Exerted by ſuch weak and contemptible <hi>Inſtruments.</hi> The Walls of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richo</hi> (the <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Spiritual</hi> wickedneſs) were thrown down by the blaſt of ſeven <hi>Rams Horns,</hi> when blown by the <hi>Prieſts</hi> whom He had commanded: And He rebuked the Iniquity of <hi>Balaam</hi> by the mouth of an <hi>Aſs,</hi> to ſhew that no <hi>Inſtruments</hi> are <hi>Ineffectual</hi> in His Hands; and made uſe of the mouth of <hi>Balaam</hi> to Propheſie of <hi>Christ.</hi> For this cauſe, ſays St. <hi>Barnabas,</hi> in his <hi>Catholick Epiſtle,</hi> c. 5.
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> did <hi>Christ</hi> chooſe Men who were <hi>Exceeding great Sinners</hi> to be His <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles;</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41791:19"/>to ſhew the Greatneſs of His <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Grace;</hi> and put the Ineſtimable <hi>Treaſure</hi> of His <hi>Goſpel</hi> into <hi>Earthen Veſſels,</hi> that the Praiſe might be to <hi>God,</hi> and not to Men.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. St. <hi>Paul</hi> rejoyced in <hi>Christ</hi> being Preached,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ihil.</hi> i. 16.</note> tho' <hi>not ſincerely</hi> by thoſe who did it; becauſe God can bring <hi>Good</hi> out of <hi>Evil;</hi> and by wicked <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> Propagate His <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;</hi> turning their <hi>malice</hi> (even of the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf) to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of the <hi>Faith:</hi> Otherwiſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> cou'd have no cauſe to <hi>Rejoyce</hi> in the Preaching of <hi>wicked</hi> Men, if none cou'd receive benefit by it. And he plainly ſuppoſes, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> ix. 27. That a Man may ſave others by his <hi>Preaching,</hi> and yet himſelf be a <hi>caſt-away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. And ſo far as we can know or judge any thing, we ſee daily Experience of this; That God has touched Mens Hearts upon hearing the <hi>Truth</hi> ſpoken, tho' by Men who were great <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and very <hi>Wicked.</hi> And what reaſon can be given to the contrary? <hi>Truth</hi> is <hi>Truth</hi> whoever ſpeaks it: And if my Heart be prepared, the <hi>good Seed</hi> receives no evil <hi>Tincture</hi> of the Hand that ſowed it: And who can Limit <hi>God,</hi> that His <hi>Grace</hi> may not go along with me in this?</p>
               <p>I have heard ſome of the <hi>now ſeparate Quakers</hi> confeſs, that they have formerly felt very ſenſible Operations of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> upon the <hi>Preaching</hi> of ſome of thoſe whom they have ſince Detected of <hi>groſs Errors</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſies;</hi> and they now think it ſtrange. But this were enough to convince them, that <hi>the wind bloweth where it liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:</hi> otherwiſe they muſt condemn themſelves, and confeſs that, in all that time, they had no true Participation of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, but that what they miſtook for it, was a meer <hi>Deluſion:</hi> Or elſe confeſs that by the <hi>Truths</hi> which were ſpoken by theſe <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> (for they ſpeak <hi>ſome</hi> Truths) <hi>God</hi> might work a good Effect upon the Hearts of ſome <hi>Well-diſpos'd,</hi> tho' then <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> and much <hi>Deluded</hi> People. If not ſo, we muſt judge very ſeverely of all thoſe who live in <hi>Idolatrous</hi> or <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; ther were <hi>great Prophets</hi> and <hi>good Men</hi> among the <hi>Ten Tribes.</hi> And if the <hi>Words,</hi> nay <hi>Miracles,</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> did render the Hearts of many yet more obdurate,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> xii. from <hi>v.</hi> 22. to <hi>v.</hi> 32.</note> even to ſin againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> which was the reaſon why He ſometimes refus'd to work <hi>Miracles</hi> among them, becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they grew worſe and worſe; and if the Preaching of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> by the mouths of <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> became the ſavour of <hi>Death</hi> to <hi>wicked</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:41791:19"/>and <hi>unprepar'd</hi> Hearts; why may not the words of <hi>Truth</hi> have a good Effect upon <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>good</hi> Minds, tho' ſpoken from the mouth of an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> or of Perſons, who, in other things, are greatly <hi>Deluded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have before mention'd the <hi>Wizard</hi> Major <hi>Weir,</hi> who <hi>Bewitched</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſince the <hi>Reſtoration,</hi> 1660, as much as <hi>Simon Mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> did the <hi>Samaritans:</hi> And yet I ſuppoſe the more moderate of the <hi>Quakers</hi> will not raſhly give all over to Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, who blindly followed him, and admir'd his <hi>Gifts;</hi> or will ſay but that ſome words of Truth he might drop, might have a real good Effect upon ſome <hi>Well meaning,</hi> tho' groſly <hi>Deluded</hi> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who followed him. Two of <hi>Winder</hi>'s <hi>Witches</hi> (ſee <hi>The Snake in the Graſs,</hi> p. 300. 2d. Edit.) were <hi>Preachers</hi> among the <hi>Quakers</hi> for Twenty years together; and thought to be as <hi>Powerful</hi> and <hi>Affecting</hi> as any others.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. But, the Argument will hold ſtronger againſt them, as to the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> than in the Office of <hi>Preaching;</hi> becauſe in <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> much depends upon the Qualifications of the Perſon, as to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, Memory, Judgment,</hi> &amp;c. But in the Adminiſtration of an <hi>Outward Sacrament,</hi> nothing is requir'd, as of <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> but the lawfulneſs of the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> by which ſuch a Perſon does Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter; and a ſmall meaſure of <hi>natural</hi> or <hi>acquir'd</hi> Parts is ſufficient to the <hi>Adminiſtration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore let us lay no ſtreſs upon the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> (more than was upon the <hi>Waters</hi> of <hi>Jordan</hi> to heal <hi>Naaman</hi>) but truſt wholly upon the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> which conveys the <hi>Vertue</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> and not from His <hi>Miniſters:</hi> That all the <hi>Glory</hi> may be to <hi>God,</hi> and not to <hi>Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, the <hi>Perſonal</hi> Qualifications of the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> are <hi>Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>Deſirable;</hi> but they become a <hi>Snare,</hi> where we expect any part of the <hi>Succeſs</hi> from them. This was the ground of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian</hi> Schiſm (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> i. 11.) and, tho' unſeen, of ours at this Day.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. And the conſequences of it, are of manifold and fatal Deſtruction.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This unſettles all the <hi>Aſſurance</hi> wee in have in God's <hi>Promiſe</hi> to aſſiſt His own <hi>Inſtitution;</hi> for, if the <hi>Vertue,</hi> or any part of it, lies in the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> we can never be ſure of the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41791:20"/>Effect, as to us; becauſe, we have no <hi>certain</hi> knowledge of the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of another. <hi>Hypocrites</hi> deceive even <hi>good Men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This wou'd quite diſappoint the <hi>Promiſe</hi> Chriſt has made, <hi>Matth.</hi> xxviii. 20. To be with His <hi>Miniſters,</hi> in the Execution of His Commiſſion; to <hi>Baptize, &amp;c. always, even unto the end of the world.</hi> For, if the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Inſtrument</hi> be a <hi>neceſſary</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification, this may fail, nay always muſt fail, ſo far as we can be <hi>ſure</hi> of it; and conſequently <hi>Chriſt</hi> has commanded <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and <hi>His Supper</hi> to continue, <hi>to the end of the world,</hi> till <hi>his coming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain;</hi> and yet has not afforded <hi>means</hi> whereby they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd; which He has not done, if the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> be a <hi>neceſſary</hi> Qualification; and that He has not left us a <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> Rule, whereby to judge of the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of another: And thus have you rendred the <hi>Command</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> of none Effect, thro' your Tradition.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This is contrary to all God's former Inſtitutions. The <hi>wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> did not <hi>excuſe</hi> any of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from bringing of their <hi>Sacrifices</hi> to the <hi>Prieſts:</hi> The <hi>Prieſts</hi> were to Anſwer for their own Sin, but the <hi>People</hi> were not anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for it, or their <hi>Offerings</hi> the leſs accepted.</p>
               <p>But we were in a much worſe condition, under the <hi>Goſpel Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration,</hi> if the Effect of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Inſtitutions, did depend either <hi>wholly,</hi> or in <hi>part</hi> upon the <hi>Perſonal Holineſs</hi> of His <hi>Prieſts.</hi> This wou'd put us much more in their Power, than it is the Intention of thoſe who make this objection to allow to them: This mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>Men,</hi> more than is due to them; therefore I will apply the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s wolds to this Caſe;
<note place="margin">1 Cor. iii. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Let no man glory in men; who is Paul? and who is Apollo? but miniſters—ſo then, neither is he that planteth any thing, neither he that watereth; but God who giveth the increaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. This was (with others) the Error of the Ancient <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> thoſe Proud and Turbulent <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> the great <hi>Diſturbers</hi> of the <hi>Peace</hi> of the Church, upon an opinion of their own <hi>Sanctity,</hi> above that of other Men: For which reaſon, they rejected all <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſms,</hi> except what was performed by themſelves; and <hi>Re-baptiz'd</hi> thoſe who came over to them, from the <hi>Church;</hi> for, they ſaid that the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrator</hi> was <hi>neceſſary</hi> towards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying the <hi>Spiritual Graces</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> Thus they argu'd; <hi>Qui non habet quod Det, quomodo Dat?</hi> i.e. <hi>How ſhall a Man give that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41791:20"/>to another, which he has not himſelf?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Adv. <hi>Parmen.</hi> l. 5. de ſchiſmat. Donatiſt Ed. <hi>Paris</hi> 1631. p 87</note> But <hi>Optatus</hi> Anſwers them, that <hi>God</hi> was the <hi>Giver,</hi> and not <hi>Man, Videte Deumeſſe Datorem.</hi> And he argues that it was preferring <hi>Themſelves</hi> before <hi>God,</hi> to think that the <hi>Vertue</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm</hi> did come from <hi>Them;</hi> that they were nothing but <hi>Miniſters</hi> or <hi>Work-men;</hi> and that, as when a <hi>Cloth</hi> was <hi>Dyed,</hi> the <hi>change</hi> of the <hi>Cloth</hi> came from the <hi>Colours</hi> infus'd, not from the vertue of the <hi>Dyer.</hi> So that in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> the <hi>Change</hi> of the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized,</hi> came from the <hi>Vertue</hi> of the <hi>Sacrament;</hi> not from the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator:</hi> That it was the <hi>Water</hi> of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which did <hi>waſh,</hi> not the Perſon who apply'd the <hi>Water.</hi> That the <hi>Perſonal Sanctity</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrator</hi> ſignify'd nothing to the <hi>Efficacy</hi> of the <hi>Sacrament;</hi> Therefore, ſays he, <hi>Nos operemur ut Ille det,
<note place="margin">p. 88.</note> qui ſe daturum eſſe promiſit,</hi> i.e. <hi>Let us work, that God, who has promis'd it, may beſtow the Effect:</hi> And that when we work, <hi>Humana ſunt opera, ſed Dei ſunt Munera,</hi> i. e. The <hi>Work</hi> is <hi>Man's,</hi> but the <hi>Gift</hi> is <hi>God's.</hi> And thence he expoſes that Ridiculous Principle of the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam illud quam Ridiculum est, quod, quaſi ad Gloriam veſtram, à vobis ſemper auditur, hoc munus Baptiſmatis, eſt Dantis, non Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipient is?</hi> p. 89.</note> which they advanc'd to gain <hi>Glory</hi> to <hi>Themſelves;</hi> that the <hi>Gift</hi> in <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was of the <hi>Adminiſtrator,</hi> and not of the <hi>Receiver:</hi> But he ſhews, that the <hi>Gift</hi> was conferred by <hi>God,</hi> proportionably to the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver,</hi> and not according to the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Diſcourſe is large, to which I refer the Reader. I have given this Taſt of it, to let theſe ſee to whom I now write, that they have (tho' unaware) ſtumbled upon the very Notion of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> which divided them from the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> and which, with them, has been, long ſince, Exploded by the whole <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> World; and I hope this may bring them to a more ſober mind; to conſider <hi>from whence,</hi> and <hi>with whom</hi> they have fallen; and to return again to the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the Participation of the Bleſſed <hi>Sacraments</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Ineſtimable <hi>Benefits</hi> which He has promis'd to the <hi>Worthy Receivers</hi> of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Let me obſerve that this <hi>Error</hi> of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> and <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> borders near upon <hi>Popery;</hi> nay rather ſeems to exceed it. For the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Modern Rome</hi> makes the <hi>Validity</hi> of the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to depend upon the <hi>Intention</hi> of the <hi>Prieſt;</hi> but his <hi>Intention</hi> is much more in his own Power; and ther are more evident <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> of it than of his <hi>Holineſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41791:21"/>
               <p n="8">VIII. I wou'd not have the <hi>Quakers</hi> imagine that any thing I have ſaid was meant in excuſe for the ill Lives of the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> as if the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> were unblamable, but our <hi>Clergy</hi> wholly Proſtitute to all wickedneſs; and that for this cauſe, we plead againſt the <hi>Sanctity</hi> of the <hi>Adminiſtrator,</hi> as Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to the <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No, That is far from the Reaſon: I do not love to make compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or Perſonal Reflections. If all Men be not as they ſhou'd be, pray God make them ſo. But I think ther is no modeſt <hi>Diſſenter</hi> will be offended, if I ſay, that ther are of our <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> Men, not only of <hi>Learning,</hi> and <hi>moral Honeſty,</hi> but of <hi>Devotion,</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual illumination;</hi> and as much of the <hi>Sobriety</hi> of Religion; and can give as many <hi>Signs</hi> of it, Equally at leaſt (to ſpeak mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly) as any of our <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> of what Denomination ſoever.</p>
               <p n="9">IX. And I hope, that what I have ſaid will, at leaſt, hinder the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> to be any <hi>Objection</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: And they being poſſeſs'd moreover of all the other <hi>Pretences</hi> of our <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> the Ballance muſt needs lie on their ſide, and <hi>ſecurity</hi> can only be with them; becauſe ther is <hi>doubt</hi> in all the other <hi>Schemes</hi> of the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> if what I have ſaid can amount but to a <hi>Doubt.</hi> If the want of <hi>Succeſſion</hi> and <hi>outward Commiſſion,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which <hi>Chriſt</hi> and His <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the whole <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> in all Ages, till the laſt <hi>Century;</hi> and in all Places, even at this Day, except ſome <hi>Corners</hi> in the <hi>west;</hi> and the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before them, did, by the Expreſs Command of God, lay ſo great a ſtreſs; if all this make but a <hi>Doubt</hi> (it is ſtrange that it ſhou'd, at leaſt, that it ſhou'd not) in the mind of any conſidering Perſons; then can they not, with <hi>Security,</hi> Communicate with any of our <hi>Diſſenters;</hi> becauſe, if he that <hi>Eateth</hi> and <hi>Doubteth</hi> is <hi>Damned,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> xiv. 23.</note> much more he that ſhall do ſo in <hi>Religious</hi> matters; wherein chiefly this Rule muſt ſtand, that <hi>whatſoever is not of Faith is ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">X. But now, to argue a little, <hi>ad hominem,</hi> ſuppoſe that the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of our <hi>Biſhops</hi> were loſt; and ſuppoſe, what the <hi>Quakers</hi> and ſome others wou'd have, that the Thread being broke, we muſt caſt a new knot, and begin again, and make an Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment amongſt our ſelves, the beſt we can. Well, When this is done, ought not that <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> to be preſerv'd? Ought eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to break in upon it, without juſt cauſe? Shou'd every
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:41791:21"/>one take upon him (or <hi>her</hi>) to <hi>Preach,</hi> or <hi>Baptize,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Rules</hi> Eſtabliſh'd? This, I think, no <hi>Society</hi> of Men will allow; For, the Members of a <hi>Society</hi> muſt be ſubject to the <hi>Rules</hi> of the <hi>Society,</hi> otherwiſe it is no <hi>Society:</hi> And the <hi>Quakers</hi> of <hi>Grace-church-ſtreet</hi> Communion have contended as Zealouſly for this compliance as any.</p>
               <p>Now then, ſuppoſe that the conſcientious <hi>Quakers</hi> to whom I ſpeak, ſhou'd lay no ſtreſs at all upon the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of our <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and conſider our <hi>Conſtitution</hi> no otherwiſe than of an <hi>Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment</hi> by agreement amongſt our ſelves; yet even ſo, by their own Confeſſion, while they can find no fault with our <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Worſhip,</hi> they ought not to make a <hi>Schiſm</hi> in this <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> which they found <hi>Eſtabliſhed;</hi> and they ought to return to it; and if a new <hi>Knot</hi> was caſt upon the broken <hi>Thread</hi> of <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> at the <hi>Reformation</hi> from <hi>Popery,</hi> that <hi>Knot</hi> ought not to be un-loſed, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out apparent and abſolute <hi>Neceſſity;</hi> leſt if we caſt new <hi>Knots</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Day, we ſhall have no <hi>Thread</hi> left <hi>un-knotted;</hi> and expoſe our ſelves to the Deriſion of the common Adverſary.</p>
               <p n="11">XI. Conſider the grievous Sin of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Diviſion;</hi> it is no leſs than the Rending of <hi>Chriſt's Body;</hi> and therefore <hi>great Things</hi> ought to be born, rather than run into it; even <hi>all things,</hi> except only that which is <hi>apparently ſinful;</hi> and that by the <hi>Expreſs words</hi> of <hi>Scripture;</hi> and not from our own Imaginations, tho' never ſo ſtrong. And tho' ther are ſome Imperſections in our <hi>Reformation,</hi> as to <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and all the <hi>High Places</hi> are not yet taken away (the Lord, of His Mercy, quickly remove them) yet I will be bold to ſay, that in our <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> nothing can be objected that is contrary to the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> or any thing Enjoyn'd, which is <hi>There</hi> Forbid to be done: And nothing leſs can warrant any <hi>Schiſm</hi> againſt our <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">XII. Now, to come to a Concluſion, upon the whole matter. If you cannot get <hi>Baptiſm</hi> as you wou'd have it, take it as you can get it. If you cannot find Men of ſuch <hi>Perſonal</hi> Excellencies as the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> take thoſe who have the ſame <hi>Commiſſion</hi> which they had, deriv'd down to them by regular <hi>Ordination;</hi> who <hi>Reform'd</hi> from <hi>Popery,</hi> and have been the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Church</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> ever ſince: And moreover are as un-exceptionable, in their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Converſations,</hi> as any others. Theſe are all the ſecurities you can have (without new <hi>Miracles</hi>) for Receiving the <hi>Sacraments</hi> from Proper hands. And therefore ther is no doubt but God will accept
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41791:22"/>of your <hi>Obedience</hi> in Receiving them from ſuch hands; much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than your <hi>Diſobedience</hi> of His Command to be <hi>Baptized,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you are not pleas'd with thoſe whom His Providence has, at this Day, left in the Execution of His Commiſſion to <hi>Baptize;</hi> as if the weakneſs of His <hi>Miniſter</hi> cou'd obſtruct the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of His <hi>Spirit,</hi> in making good His part of the Covenant, which He has promiſed.</p>
               <p n="13">XIII. Ther is an Objection againſt <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> which is not worth an Anſwer; but that I wou'd condeſcend to the meaneſt, and leave nothing behind which might be a ſtumbling block to any.</p>
               <p>I have heard it urg'd, that ther is no viſible Effects ſeen by our <hi>Baptiſms;</hi> that Men remain <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>looſe</hi> notwithſtanding; and therefore ſome do conclude that ther is no vertue in <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To make this Argument of any force, it muſt be prov'd that <hi>none</hi> do receive any Benefit by it. For, if <hi>ſome</hi> do receive Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by it, and <hi>others</hi> do not, this muſt be charg'd upon the <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> of the <hi>Recipient;</hi> according to the known Rule, that <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is receiv'd, is receiv'd according to the diſpoſition of the Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> Thus the ſame <hi>Meat</hi> is turn'd into <hi>good Nouriſhment</hi> in an <hi>healthy,</hi> and into <hi>noxious Humors</hi> in a <hi>vitiated Stomach. Simon Magus</hi> receiv'd no Benefit by his <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> and after the <hi>Sop</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> entred into <hi>Judas;</hi> yet the other <hi>Apoſtles</hi> receiv'd great Benefit by it:
<note place="margin">1 Cor. x. 16. c. xi. 29.</note> To ſome it is the ſavour of <hi>Life,</hi> even the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of <hi>Chriſt's Body</hi> and <hi>Blood;</hi> to others of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation,</hi> who <hi>diſcern not the Lord's Body</hi> in it, but receive it as a common thing: Therefore we are commanded to <hi>examine</hi> our ſelves,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 28.</note> to <hi>prepare</hi> our <hi>Hearts</hi> for the <hi>worthy</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of it.</p>
               <p>But ſome ſay, as the <hi>Jews</hi> to <hi>Chriſt, ſhew us a ſign:</hi> They wou'd have ſome <hi>Miraculous</hi> Effects, immediately to appear. Theſe are Ignorant of the Operations of the <hi>Spirit;</hi> and to theſe I ſay, in the words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Joh. iii. 8. <hi>The wind bloweth where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof, but canſt not tell whence it cometh or whither it goeth; ſo is every one that is born of the Spirit.</hi> It works <hi>ſilently,</hi> but <hi>powerfully;</hi> and its <hi>Progreſs,</hi> like the <hi>growing</hi> of our <hi>Bodies,</hi> is not all at once, but by Degrees; whoſe <hi>motion</hi> is Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible to humane Eyes.</p>
               <p>The true uſe that is to be made of this <hi>Objection,</hi> that ſo few (and yet they are not <hi>few</hi> who) receive the Ineſtimable Benefits which are convey'd in the <hi>Sacraments</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Inſtitution, is this,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:41791:22"/>To take the greater Care, and the more Earneſtly to beg the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of God's <hi>Grace,</hi> to <hi>fit</hi> and <hi>prepare</hi> us, for the <hi>worthy</hi> Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them; but by no means to neglect them: For thoſe who <hi>refuſed</hi> to come to the <hi>Supper</hi> were Rejected, as well as he who came without a <hi>Wedding Garment.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="supplement">
               <head>A SUPPLEMENT.</head>
               <p>THE ſtreſs of this <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> being Founded upon <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> and long <hi>Quotations</hi> being improper in ſo ſhort a method of Argument as I have taken; to ſupply that Defect, and, at the ſame time, to make it eaſier to the Reader, I have added, by way of <hi>Supplement,</hi> a ſhort <hi>Index</hi> or <hi>Collection</hi> of <hi>Authorities,</hi> in the firſt 450 Years after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Pretences, of making a <hi>Biſhop</hi> all one with a <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> at leaſt with one of their <hi>Moderators:</hi> And, in the next place, I have ſhewn the ſenſe of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> as to <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> Take them as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some Authorities for</hi> Epiſcopacy, <hi>as</hi> diſtinct <hi>from and</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior <hi>to</hi> Presbytery, <hi>taken out of the</hi> Fathers <hi>and</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, <hi>in the firſt Four Hundred and Fifty Years after</hi> Chriſt.</p>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 70. St. <hi>Clement</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Martyr,</hi> of whom mention is made <hi>Phil.</hi> iv. 3. in his 1ſt. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> N. 42. p. 89. of the Edition at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1677.</head>
                  <p>The Apoſtles having Preached the Goſpel, thro' Regions and Cities, did Conſtitute the firſt Fruits of them, having prov'd them by the Spirit, to be <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> of thoſe who ſhou'd
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:41791:23"/>believe; and this, not as a new thing, for many Ages before it was written concerning <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi> for, thus ſaith the <hi>Scripture,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> Lx 17.</note> in a certain place, <hi>I will conſtitute their</hi> Biſhops <hi>in Righteouſneſs, and their</hi> Deacons <hi>in Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What wonder is it then, that thoſe who were Intruſted by God, in Chriſt, with this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, ſhou'd Conſtitute thoſe before ſpoke of?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> n. 44. And the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> knew by the Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> that Conteſts wou'd ariſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Name (or Order) and for this Cauſe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving perfect fore knowledge (of theſe things) they did Ordain thoſe whom we have mention'd before; and moreover, did Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh, the Conſtitution, that other approved Men ſhou'd ſucceed thoſe who Dy'd, in their Office and Miniſtry.</p>
                  <p>Therefore thoſe that were Conſtituted by Them, or after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by other approved Men, with the Conſent of all the Church, and have Adminiſtred to the Block of Chriſt unblama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, with Humility and Quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, without all ſtain of filth or naughtineſs; and have carry'd a good Report, of a long time, from all Men, I think cannot, without great Injuſtice, be turn'd out of their Office: For, it will be no ſmall ſin to us, if we thruſt thoſe from their Biſhopricks who haves Holily and without Blame offer'd our Giſts (and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God.) Bleſſed are thoſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:41791:23"/>Prieſts who are happily Dead, for they are not afraid of being E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected out of the Places in which they are Conſtituted. For, I underſtand that you have Depriv'd ſome, from their Miniſtry, who behaved themſelves un-re-prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able amongſt you.</p>
                  <p>Par. 40. To the <hi>High-Priest</hi> his proper Offices were appein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; the <hi>Prieſts</hi> had their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Order, and the <hi>Levites</hi> their peculiar Services, or <hi>Deacon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips;</hi> and the <hi>Lay-men,</hi> what was proper ſer <hi>Lay-men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This, as before ſhewn, St. <hi>Clement</hi> apply'd to the Diſtribution of Orders in the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Church; <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi> And the <hi>Office</hi> of the <hi>Levites,</hi> is here cali'd by the Word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>i. e.</hi> the Office of <hi>Deacons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A.D.</hi> 71. St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> a Glorious <hi>Martyr</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> was Conſtituted, by the Apoſtles, <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,</hi> and did there by think that he ſucceeded them (as all other <hi>Biſhops</hi> do) in their full <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Office. Thence he ſalutes the Church of the <hi>Trall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ans,</hi> in the <hi>Fulneſs</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtolical Character;</hi> and in his Epiſtle he ſays to them,</p>
                  <p>Be ſubject to your Biſhop as to the Lord—</p>
                  <p>And to the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> as to the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>—Likewiſe the <hi>Deacons</hi> alſo, being <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Myſteries of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ought to pleaſe in all things—. Without theſe ther is no <hi>Church</hi> of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect-He is without, who does any thing without the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi> and ſuch an one is Deſiled in his Conſcience.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In his Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt. to the</hi> Magneſians, <hi>he tells them,</hi> That they ought not to deſpiſe their <hi>Biſhop</hi> for his youth, but to pay him all manner
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:41791:24"/>of Reverence, according to the Commandment of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And as I know that your Holy <hi>Presbyters</hi> do—</p>
                  <p>Therefore as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did nothing without the <hi>Father,</hi> ſo neither do ye, whether <hi>Presbyter, Deacon,</hi> or <hi>Laick,</hi> any thing without the <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some indeed call him <hi>Biſhop;</hi> yet do all things without him; but theſe ſeem not to me to have a good Conſcience, but rather to be Hypocrites and Scorners.</p>
                  <p>I Exhort you to do all things in the ſame mind of God, the <hi>Biſhop</hi> Preſiding in the Place of <hi>God;</hi> and the <hi>Presbyters</hi> in room of the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> and the <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi> moſt beloved to me, who are intruſted with the Miniſtry of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He directs his</hi> Epiſtle <hi>to the Church at</hi> Philadelphia, <hi>to thoſe</hi> who were in Unity with their <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſays to them, in his</hi> Epiſtle, <hi>That</hi> as many as are of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> theſe are with the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> and thoſe who ſhall Repent, and Return to the Unity of the <hi>Church,</hi> being made worthy of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſhall partake of Eternal Salvation in the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Brethren, be not deceived, if any ſhall follow himthat makes a <hi>Schiſm,</hi> he ſhall not Inherit the Kingdom of God.</p>
                  <p>I Exhort you to partake of the one <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> for ther is one <hi>Body</hi> of the Lord <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and one <hi>Blood</hi> of His, which was ſhed for us; and one <hi>Cup</hi>—and one <hi>Altar,</hi> ſo ther
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:41791:24"/>is one <hi>Biſhop,</hi> with his <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and the <hi>Deacons,</hi> my Fellow Servants.</p>
                  <p>Give heed to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and to the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and to the <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi>—Without the <hi>Biſhop</hi> do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In his Epiſtle to the</hi> Smyrneans, <hi>he ſays, Flee Diviſions as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Evils.</hi> All of them follow their <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Father;</hi> and the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the <hi>Deacons</hi> as the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>God.</hi> Let no man do any thing of what appertains to the <hi>Church,</hi> without the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> Let that <hi>Sacrament</hi> be judg'd Effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and Firm, which is Diſpenced by the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or him to whom the <hi>Biſhop</hi> has Commited it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the <hi>Biſhop</hi> is, there let the <hi>People</hi> be; as where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is, there the <hi>Heavenly Hoſt</hi> is gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together. It is not lawful, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> either to <hi>Baptize,</hi> or celebrate the <hi>Offices:</hi> But what He approves of, according to the good Pleaſure of God, that is firm and ſafe, and ſo we do every thing ſecurely.</p>
                  <p>I ſalute your moſt worthy <hi>Biſhop,</hi> your venerable <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and the <hi>Deacons</hi> my Fellow Servants.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:41791:22"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 70. St. <hi>Clement</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Martyr,</hi> of whom mention is made <hi>Phil.</hi> iv. 3. in his 1ſt. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> N. 42. p. 89. of the Edition at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1677.</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:41791:23"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:41791:23"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:41791:24"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41791:24"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>In his Epiſtle to St.</hi> Policarp, Biſhop <hi>of</hi> Smyrna, <hi>and</hi> Martyr, <hi>who, together with himſelf, was</hi> Diſciple <hi>to St.</hi> John <hi>the</hi> Apoſtle, <hi>and</hi> Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt. <hi>He gives theſe Directions.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>If any can remain in Chaſtity, to the glory of the Body of the Lord, let him remain without Boaſting, if he Boaſt, he Periſhes; and if he pretends to know more than the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:41791:25"/>
                     <hi>Biſhop</hi> he is corrupted. It is thedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty both of Men and Women that Marry, to be joyn'd together by the Approbation of the <hi>Biſh.</hi> that the Muriage may be in the Lord, and not according to our own Luſts. Let all things be done to the Glory of God.</p>
                  <p>Give heed to your <hi>Biſhop,</hi> that God may Harken unto you: My Soul for theirs, who ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the Obedience of their <hi>Biſhop, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi> and let me take my Lot with them in the Lord.</p>
                  <p>And he ſays to Biſhop <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carp, Let nothing be done without thy ſentence and approbation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:41791:24"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>In his Epiſtle to St.</hi> Policarp, Biſhop <hi>of</hi> Smyrna, <hi>and</hi> Martyr, <hi>who, together with himſelf, was</hi> Diſciple <hi>to St.</hi> John <hi>the</hi> Apoſtle, <hi>and</hi> Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt. <hi>He gives theſe Directions.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:41791:25"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>A.D.</hi> 180. St. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> who was Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of St. <hi>Polycarp;</hi> he flouriſh'd about the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 180.</head>
                  <p>We can reckon thoſe <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who have been Conſtituted by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors all the way to our times. And if the Apoſtles knew hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Myſteries, they wou'd cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly deliver them chiefly to thoſe, to whom they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Churches themſelves; and whom they left their own Succeſſors, and in the ſame Place of Government as themſelves.—We have the Succeſſions of the Biſhops, to whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Church in every place was committed. All theſe <hi>(He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks)</hi> are much later than the Biſhops, to whom the Apoſtles did deliver the Churches.</p>
                  <p>The true Knowledge is the Doctrin of the Apoſtles, and the Ancient State of the Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hrough the whole World, and the Character of the Body
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41791:25"/>of Chriſt, according to the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of the Biſhops, to whom they committed the Church that is in every Place; and which has Deſcended even unto us.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:41791:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A.D.</hi> 180. St. <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> who was Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of St. <hi>Polycarp;</hi> he flouriſh'd about the year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 180.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Advers.</hi> Haereſes. <hi>l. 3. c. 3.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Habemus muncrare qui ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolis Inſtituti ſunt Epiſcopi in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiis, &amp; ſucceſſores corum uſque ad nos. Et ſi Recondita myſteria Sc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſent Apostoli, vel his maxime traderent ea, quibus etiam ipſas Eccleſias committebant; quos &amp; ſucceſſores relinquebant, ſuum ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum locum Magiſterii tradentes.</hi> lib. 4. c. 63. <hi>Habemus ſucceſſiones Epiſcoporum quibus Apoſtolicam quae in unoquoque loco eſt Eccleſiam tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diderunt.</hi> l. 5. c. 20. <hi>Omnes enim ii (Haeretici) valde Poſteriores ſunt, quam Epiſcopi, quibus Apostoli tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diderunt Eccleſias.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>L. 4. c. 6. <hi>Agnitio vera eſt, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſtolorum Doctrina, &amp; Antiquus Eccleſia status, in univerſo Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, &amp; Character Corporis Chriſti ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundam ſucceſſiones Epiſcoporum,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:41791:25"/>quibús illi eam quae in unoquo<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> lico eſt Eccleſiam tradiderunt, quae pervenit uſque ad nos.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Tertullian,</hi> A.D. 203. of the Preſcription of <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <note place="margin">A.D. 203.</note>
                  <p>
                     <hi>c.</hi> 32. Let them produce the Original of their Churches; let them ſhew the Order of their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, that by their Succeſſion, deduc'd from the beginning, we may ſee whether their firſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop had any of the Apoſtles or Apoſtolical Men, who did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe perſevere with the Apoſtles, for his Founder and Predeceſſor. For, thus the Apoſtolical Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches do derive their Succeſſion: As the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> from <hi>Polycarp,</hi> whom <hi>John</hi> (the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) placed there: The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> from <hi>Clement,</hi> who was, in like manner, ordain'd by <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> And ſo the other Churches can produce thoſe Conſtituted in their <hi>Biſhopricks</hi> by the <hi>Apoſiles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>c.</hi> 36. Reckon over the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Churches, where the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chairs of the Apoſtles do yet Preſide in their own Places. At <hi>Corinth, Philippi, Epheſus, Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonica,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Of Baptiſm, <hi>c.</hi> 17.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> who is the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> has the Power of confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Baptiſm; and under him the <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi> but not without the Authority of the <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Origen, Names the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Orders of <hi>Biſhop, Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:41791:26"/>and <hi>Deacon.</hi> Such a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop (<hi>ſays he, ſpeaking of one who ſought vain Glory,</hi> &amp;c.) doth not deſire a good Work—and the ſame is to be ſaid of <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi>—The <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> who have the Chief Place among the People.—The <hi>Biſhop</hi> is called <hi>Prince</hi> in the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches:</hi> And ſpeaking of the Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>Clergy,</hi> he directs it to them, whether <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters,</hi> or <hi>Deacons.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:41791:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Tertullian,</hi> A.D. 203. of the Preſcription of <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Edant ergo Origines Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuarum; evolvant ordinem Epiſcoporum ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rum, ita ut per ſucceſſiones ab initio decurrentem, ut primus ille Epiſcopus aliquem ex Apoſtolis, vel Apoſtolicis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, qui tamen cum Apoſtolis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveraverit, habuerit Auctorem &amp; Anteceſſorem. Hoc emm mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Eccleſiae Apoſlolicae cenſus ſuos deferunt: ſicut</hi> Smyrneorum <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia</hi> Polycarpum <hi>ab</hi> Johanne <hi>conlocatum refert; ſicut</hi> Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum, Clementem, <hi>à</hi> Petro <hi>ordinatum itidem, Perinde utique &amp; Ceterae exhibent quos ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis in Epiſcopatum Conſlitutes Apoſtolici ſeminis traduces ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Percurre Eccleſias Apoſtolicas, apud quas ipſae adhuc Cathedrae Apoſtolorum ſuis locis Praſident.</hi> Corinthi, Philippi, Epheſiis, Theſſalonica, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dandi (Baptiſmum) jus habet ſummus ſacerdos, qui est</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copus; <hi>dehinc</hi> Presbyteri <hi>&amp;</hi> Deaconi, <hi>non tamen ſine</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi <hi>Authoritate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A. D. 220. <hi>Origenis Comment.
<note place="margin">A.D. 220.</note> in</hi> Matt. <hi>Rothomagi</hi> 1668. <hi>Gr. Lat. p.</hi> 255
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:41791:26"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>—<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>—<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 443. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. — <hi>p.</hi> 420 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. — <hi>p.</hi> 442. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> A. D. 240.<note place="margin">A.D. 240.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>Our Lord, whoſe Commands we ought to Reverence and Obey, being about to Conſtitute the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal</hi> Honour, and the Frame of His Church, ſaid to Peter, <hi>Thou art Peter,</hi> &amp;c. From thence the Order of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Church does deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend, by the line of Succeſſion, thro' all Times and Ages; that the Church ſhou'd be built upon the <hi>Biſhops</hi>—It is Eſtabliſh'd by the Divine Law, that every Act of the Church ſhou'd be Govern'd by the Biſhop. <hi>To</hi> Cornelius, <hi>then Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We ought chiefly (my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to Endeavour to keep that Unity which was Enjoyn'd by our Lord and His Apoſtles to us their Succeſſors, to be careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerv'd by us.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Deacons</hi> ought to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that it was the <hi>Lord</hi> who choſe the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> that is, the <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and by that, to all <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:41791:26"/>of His Church, who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> by vicarious Ordination, and are in their ſtead, <hi>He that heareth you, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For from hence do Schiſms and Hereſies ariſe, and have ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, while the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> who is <hi>One,</hi> and <hi>Governour</hi> of the Church, by a proud Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is Deſpis'd; and that Man who is Honour'd as Worthy by God, is accounted unworthy by Man.</p>
                  <p>Nor are Hereſies ſprung up, or Schiſms ariſen from any other Fountain than from hence, that Obedience is not paid to the <hi>Prieſt</hi> of God; and that ther is not one <hi>Prieſt</hi> at a time in the Church, and one Judge for the time in the Place of Chriſt. To whom if the whole Fraternity did obey, according to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oeconomy, none wou'd dare to move any thing againſt the <hi>Sacerdotal Colledge</hi>—It is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſhou'd ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ert their Authority with full Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor—But if it is ſo, that we are afraid of the Boldneſs of the moſt Profligat; and that which theſe wicked Men cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs by the Methods of Truth and Equity, if they can accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh by their Raſhneſs and Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, then is ther an end of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Authority, and of their <hi>Sublime</hi> and <hi>Divine Power</hi> in Governing of the <hi>Church.</hi> Nor
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:41791:27"/>can we remain <hi>Chriſtians</hi> any longer, if it is come to this, that we ſhou'd be afraid of the <hi>Threats,</hi> and <hi>Snares</hi> of the <hi>Wicked</hi>—</p>
                  <p>—The Adverſary of Chriſt, and Enemy of His Church, for this end ſtrikes at the <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Ruler</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> with all his Malice, that the <hi>Governor</hi> being taken away, he might Ravage the more Violently and Cruelly upon the Ship-wreck of the Church—</p>
                  <p>Is Honour then given to God, when the Divine Majeſty and Cenſure is ſo Deſpiſed, that theſe Sacrilegious Perſons ſay; do not think of the Wrath of God, be not afraid of His Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, do not knock at the Door of the Church; but without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Repentance, or Confeſſion of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Crime, Deſpiſing the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of their <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and tram<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pling it under their feet, a Falſe Peace is Preach'd to be had from the <hi>Presbyters (Scilicet)</hi> in their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon them to Admit thoſe that were <hi>Fallen</hi> into <hi>Communion,</hi> or the <hi>Peace</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> without the Allowance of the <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They imitate the coming of Anti-Chriſt now approaching.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Valerian</hi> (the Emperor wrote to the Senate, that the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and the <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> ſhou'd be proſecuted.</p>
                  <p>The Power of Remitting Sins, was given to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and to the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> who have ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them by a vicarious Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:41791:27"/>
                  <p>What Danger ought we to fear from the Diſpleaſure of God, when ſome <hi>Presbyters,</hi> neither mindful of the Goſpel, nor of their own Station in the Church, neither regarding the future Judgment of God, nor the <hi>Biſhop</hi> who is ſet over them, which was never done under our Predeceſſors, with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Neglect of their <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> do arrogate all unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? I cou'd bear with the Contempt of our <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but ther is now no room left for Diſſembling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:41791:26"/>
                  <head>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> A. D. 240.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Edit. Oxon. Epiſt. XXXIII. Lapſis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dominus noſter, cujus Praecepta metuere &amp; obſervare debemus, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi honorem &amp; Eccleſiae ſuae Ratio nem diſponens, in Evangelio loquitur &amp; dicit Petro,</hi> Ego dico tibi quia tues Petrus, <hi>&amp;c. Inde per temporum &amp; ſucceſſionum vices Epiſcoprum Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatio &amp; Ecclaeſiae Ratio decurrit, ut Ecclaeſia ſuper Epiſcopos Conſtitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur—Divina Lege fundatum eſt, ut omnis actus Ecclaeſiae per Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copum Gubernetur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ep. XLV. Cornelio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hoc enim vel maxime, Frater, &amp; laboramus &amp; laborare debemus, ut Unitatem à Domino, &amp; per A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolos nobis Succeſſoribi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, quantum poſſumus obtinere curemus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ep. III. Rogatiano.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Meminiſſe autem Diaconi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent quoniam Apoſtolos, id eſt Epiſcopos Dominus Elegit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ep. LXVI. Florentio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dixit Chriſtus ad Apoſtolos, ac
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:41791:26"/>per hoc, ad omnes Praepoſitos, qui Apoſtolis vicaria ordinatione ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt,</hi> Qui vos audit, me au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.—</p>
                  <p>Ibid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Inde enim Schiſmata &amp; Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ortae &amp; oriuntur, dum Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus qui units eſt, &amp; Eccleſiae Prae-eſt, ſuperba Praeſumptione contemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; homo dignatione Dei ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noratus, Indignus hominibus judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ep. LIX. Cornelio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Neque enim aliunde Haereſes obortae ſunt, aut nata ſunt ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata, quam inde quod</hi> Sacerdoti <hi>Dei non obtemperatur; nec unus in Eccleſia ad tempus</hi> Sacerdos, <hi>&amp; ad tempus</hi> Judex <hi>vice</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti <hi>cogitatur: Cui ſi ſecundum Magiſteria Divina obtemperaret Fraternitas univerſa, nemo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus</hi> ſacerdotum Collegium <hi>quicquam moveret — vigore pleno</hi> Epiſcopos <hi>agere oportet — quod ſi ita res eſt ut Nequiſſimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum timeatur Audacia, &amp; quod Maelt vere atque aequitate non poſſunt, Temeritate &amp; Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione perficiant; actum est de</hi> Epiſcopatus <hi>vigore, &amp; de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſie gubernandae ſublimi ac Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina Poteſtate. Nec Chriſtiani ultra aut durare aut eſſe jam poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus, ſi ad hoc ventum est, ut Perditorum Minas atque Infidias pertimeſcamus</hi> —</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:41791:27"/>
                  <p>— <hi>Chriſti Adverſarius &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae ejus Inimicus, ad hoc Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae</hi> Praepoſitum <hi>ſua Infeſtatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne perſequitur, ut</hi> Gubernatore <hi>ſublato, atrocius atque violentius circa Eccleſiae Naufragia graſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> —</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Honor ergo datur Deo, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſic Dei Majeſtas &amp; Cenſura Contemnitur— ut proponatur à Sacrilegis atque dicatur; ne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta cogitetur Dei, ne timeatur Judicium Domini, ne pulſetur ad Eccleſiam Chriſti, ſed ſubla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Poenitentia, nec ulla Exomolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſi Criminis facta, Deſpectis</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopis <hi>atque Calcatis, Pax à</hi> Presbyteris <hi>verbis fallacibus Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicetur?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>ibid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Antichriſti jam propinquantis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum Imitantur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ep. LXXX. Succeſſo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reſcripſiſſe valerianum ad Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ut Epiſcopi, &amp; Presbyteri, &amp; Diacones in continenti animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firmillanus Cypriano. Ep. LXXV. p. 225.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Poteſtas ergo Peccatorum remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendorum Apostolis data eſt— &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopis qui eis Ordinatione vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſucceſſerunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:41791:27"/>
                  <p>Ep. XVI. p. 36. Cyprianus Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteris &amp; Diaconibus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quod enim periculum metuere non debemus de offenſa Domini; quando aliqui de Presbyteris, nec Evangelu, nec Deci ſue memores, ſed ne que futurum Domini Judicium; neque ſibi praepoſitum</hi> Epiſcopum <hi>cogitantes, quod nunquam om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino ſub Anteceſſorthus factum eſt, cum Contumelia &amp; Contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Praepoſiti totum ſibi vendicent? Contumeliam</hi> Epiſcopatus <hi>noſtri diſſimulare &amp; ferre poſſum— ſed diſſimulandi nunc locus non eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Optatus Milevitanus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Mileve,</hi> or <hi>Mela</hi> in <hi>Numidia</hi> in <hi>Africa.</hi> A. D. 365.</head>
                  <note place="margin">A.D. 365</note>
                  <p>In his 2d. Book againſt <hi>Parme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</hi> The Church has her ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Members, <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters, Deacons,</hi> and the Company of the Faithful.</p>
                  <p>You found in the Church, <hi>Deacons, Presbyters, Biſhops,</hi> you have made them <hi>Lay-men;</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that you have Subverted Souls.</p>
                  <p>St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Milan.</hi> A. D. 370. upon <hi>Eph.</hi> iv. 11. <hi>Speaking of the ſeveral Orders of the Church. And he gave ſome</hi> Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and Evangeliſts, &amp;c. <hi>Says,</hi> that by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> there were meant the <hi>Biſhops;</hi> by <hi>Prophets,</hi> the Expounders of the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> and by the <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> the <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</hi> But ſays that they all met in the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> for that he was the <hi>Chief Prieſt,</hi> that is,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:41791:28"/>
                     <hi>(ſays he)</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and both <hi>Prophet</hi> and <hi>Evangeliſt,</hi> to ſupply all the Offices of the Church for the Miniſtry of the Faithful.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And upon</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> xii. 28. <hi>ſays</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> Conſtituted the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Head</hi> in the <hi>Church;</hi> and that theſe are the <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And upon <hi>v.</hi> 29. <hi>are all Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles?</hi> i.e. all are not <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> This is true <hi>(ſays he,)</hi> becauſe in the Church ther is but one <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And becauſe all things are from one God the Father, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath He appointed that one <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſhou'd Preſide over Each Church.</p>
                  <p>In his Book of the <hi>Dignity</hi> of the <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> c. 3. <hi>he ſays,</hi> That ther is nothing in this World to be found more <hi>Excellent</hi> than the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> nothing more <hi>Sublime</hi> than the <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſpeaking of what was Incumbent upon the ſeveral Orders of the <hi>Church,</hi> he does plainly diſtinguiſh them: For, ſays he, in the ſame place;</p>
                  <p>God does require one thing from a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> another from a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> another from a <hi>Deacon,</hi> and another from a <hi>Lay-man.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:41791:27"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Optatus Milevitanus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Mileve,</hi> or <hi>Mela</hi> in <hi>Numidia</hi> in <hi>Africa.</hi> A. D. 365.</head>
                  <p>l. 2. Contra Parmenianum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Certa Membra ſua habet Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia,</hi> Epiſcopos, Presbyteros, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aconos, <hi>&amp; turbam Fidelium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Inveniſtis</hi> Diaconos, Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros, Epiſcopos. <hi>feciſiis La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cos; ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcite vos animas evertiſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quoſdam dedit Apoſtolos,
<note place="margin">A.D. 37<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> Prophetas, <hi>&amp;c. Apoſtoli,</hi> Epiſcopi <hi>ſunt: Prophetae Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natores ſunt Scripturum ſicut</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabus—<hi>Evangeliſt.</hi> Diaconi <hi>ſunt, ſicut fuit</hi> Philippus—<hi>Nam in</hi> Epiſcopo <hi>omnes ordines ſunt, quia</hi> Princeps Sacerdos <hi>eſt, hoc eſt,</hi> Princeps <hi>eſt</hi> Sacerdotum, &amp; Propheta, &amp; Evangeliſta, <hi>&amp; Caetera adimplenda offic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae in Miniſterio Eideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:41791:28"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caput in Eccleſia</hi> Apoſtolos <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit—Ipſi ſunt</hi> Epiſcopi.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Verum eſt, quia in Eccleſia unus</hi> Epiſcopus <hi>eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quia ab uno Deo Patre ſunt om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, ſingulos Epiſcopos, ſingulis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiis Prae-eſſe Decrevit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>De Dignat. Sacerdot. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>ut oſtenderemus nihil eſſe in hoc ſeculo Excellentius</hi> Sacerdotibus, <hi>nihil Sublimius</hi> Epiſcopis <hi>repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riri.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aliud eſt enim quod ab</hi> Epiſcopo <hi>requirit Deus &amp; aliud quod à</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytero, <hi>&amp; aliud quod à</hi> Deacono, <hi>&amp; aliud quod à</hi> Laico.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>St. <hi>Jerom,</hi>
A. D. 380. <note place="margin">A. D. 380.</note>In his Comment upon the Ep. to <hi>Titus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>When it began to be ſaid, <hi>I am of Paul, I of Apollos,</hi> &amp;c. and every one thought that thoſe whom he Baptized, belong'd to himſelf, and not to Chriſt; it was Decreed thro' <hi>The whole Earth,</hi> that one Choſen from among the <hi>Presbyters</hi> ſhou'd be ſet over the reſt, that the Seeds of <hi>Schiſm</hi> might be taken away.</p>
                  <p>In his <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to <hi>Evagrius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From <hi>Mark</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> to <hi>Heraclas,</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> the <hi>Presbyters</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi> have
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41791:28"/>always choſen out one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, whom hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plac'd in an higher Degree than the reſt, they called their <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that is Advanc'd, is Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd from leſs to greater.</p>
                  <p>The Greatneſs of Riches, or the Humility of Poverty does not make a <hi>Biſhop</hi> greater or leſs, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>all</hi> of them are the <hi>Succeſſors</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That we may know the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical Oeconomy to be taken from the Pattern of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, the ſame that <hi>Aaron,</hi> and his <hi>Sons,</hi> and the <hi>Levites</hi> were in the <hi>Temple,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> are in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To <hi>Nepotianus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Be ſubject to your <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Chief-Prieſt;</hi> and receive him as the Father of your Soul.</p>
                  <p>Againſt the <hi>Luciferians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſafety of the Ch. depends upon the Dignity of the <hi>High-Prieſt,</hi> to whom unleſs a ſort of abſolute and eminent Power be given above all, ther will be as many <hi>Schiſms</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> as ther are <hi>Prieſts.</hi> Thence it is, that without the Command of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> neither a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> nor a <hi>Deacon,</hi> have Power to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize—And the <hi>Biſhop</hi> is to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Hands upon thoſe who are Baptized by <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi> for the Invocation of the Holy Spirit.</p>
                  <p>And Comforting <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> upon the Death of <hi>Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:41791:29"/>his <hi>Presbyter</hi> and his <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew,</hi> he Commends <hi>Nepotian</hi> in that he <hi>Reverenc'd his Biſhop.</hi> He Honour'd <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> in publick as his <hi>Biſhop,</hi> at home as his Father. But among his <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Co-equals,</hi> he was the firſt in his Vocation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon the 60th. of <hi>Iſa.</hi> He calls the future <hi>Biſhops, Princes</hi> of the Church.</p>
                  <p>Of the Eccleſiaſtical Writers. Concerning <hi>James.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>James,</hi> after the Paſſion of our Lord, was immediatly, by the Apoſtles, ordained Biſhop of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. The like he tells of the firſt Biſhops of other Places.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Epiſt. 54. againſt <hi>Montanus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>With us the <hi>Biſhops</hi> hold the Place of the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:41791:28"/>
                  <head>St. <hi>Jerom,</hi>
A. D. 380. <note place="margin">A. D. 380.</note>In his Comment upon the Ep. to <hi>Titus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Poſtquam unuſquiſque eos quos Baptizabat ſuos putabat eſſe non Chriſti,</hi> IN TOTO ORBE <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretum eſt, ut unus de</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris <hi>Electus ſuperponeretur Caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, ut Schiſmatum ſemina tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> Marco <hi>Evangeliſta ad</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclum <hi>uſq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ad</hi> Dionyſium <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos, Presbyrari</hi> Aegypti <hi>ſemper u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ex ſe Electum, in Cleſiori Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:41791:28"/>collocatum</hi> Epiſcopum <hi>Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Qui provehitur, à Minori ad Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus provehitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Potentia Divitiarum &amp; Pauper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis Humilitas, ſublimiorum vel inferiorem</hi> Epiſcopum <hi>non facit, Ceterum Omnes</hi> Apoſtolorum <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſores ſunt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ut ſciamus Traditiones Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas ſumptas de veteri Teſtamento: Quod</hi> Aaron, &amp; Filii <hi>ejus at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>
                     </hi> Levitae <hi>in</hi> Templo <hi>fuerunt, hoc ſibi</hi> Epiſcopi, Presbyteri, &amp; Deaconi, <hi>vendicent in</hi> Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ad</hi> Nepotianum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eſto ſujectus</hi> Pontiſici <hi>tuo; &amp; quaſi animi</hi> Parentem <hi>ſuſcipe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adverſ.</hi> Luciferianos.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ecclaeſiae ſalus in</hi> ſummi Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotis <hi>Dignitate pendet, cui ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi exors quaedam &amp; ab emnibus Eminens detur Poteſtas, tot in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claeſia efficientur Schiſmata quot Sacerdotes. Inde venit, ut ſine</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi <hi>juſſione neque</hi> Presbyter <hi>neque</hi> Diaconus <hi>jus haebeant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizandi—Ad eos qui per</hi> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teros &amp; Diaconos <hi>Baptizati ſunt,</hi> Epiſcopus <hi>ad Invocationem ſancti Spiritus manum Impoſiturus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epitaphium</hi> Nepotiani <hi>à</hi> Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum, <hi>Epiſcopum venerebatur —
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:41791:29"/>In publico</hi> Epiſcopum, <hi>domi Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem noverat—Inter</hi> Presbyteros <hi>&amp; Co-aequales, primus in opere,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Principes futuros Eccleſiae</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copos <hi>Nominavit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In ſcript. Eccleſiaſt. De</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobo.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jacobus poſt Paſſionem Domini ſtatim ab Apoſtolis Hieroſolimorum</hi> Epiſcopus <hi>eſt ordinatus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 54, <hi>contra</hi> Montanum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Apud nos</hi> Apoſtolorum <hi>locum</hi> Epiſcopi <hi>tenent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>St. Auguſtine <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Hippo</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> A. D. 420. Epiſtle 42.</head>
                  <note place="margin">A. D. 420.</note>
                  <p>The Root of the Chriſtian So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety is diffus'd throughout the World, in a ſure Propagation, by the Seats of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the Succeſſion of the <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt. veter. &amp; novi Teſt.</hi> N. 97.</p>
                  <p>Ther is none but knows that our Saviour did Conſtitute <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> in the Churches; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore He Aſcended into Heaven, He laid His Hands upon the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> and Ordained them <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>l. 7. c. 43. The Sentence of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is clear, who ſent His Apoſtles, and gave to <hi>Them alone</hi> that Power which He had Received from His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41791:29"/>to whom we have Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, Governing the Church of God by the ſame Power.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ep.</hi> 162. <hi>ſpeaking of the</hi> Biſhops <hi>being call'd</hi> Angels. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. <hi>he ſays,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the voice of God, the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor</hi> of the Church is Praiſed, under the Name of an <hi>Angel. Of the words of our Lord,</hi> Serm. 24.</p>
                  <p>If He ſaid to the Apoſtles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, <hi>he that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me,</hi> then deſpiſe us: But if thoſe words of His come down even unto us, and that He has Called us, and Conſtituted us in their Place, ſee that you do not deſpiſe us.</p>
                  <p>Againſt <hi>Fauſtus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We embrace the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which from the Times of the Preſence of Chriſt himſelf, by the Diſpoſition of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and the Succeſſions of other <hi>Biſhops</hi> from their Seats, even to theſe Times, has come down to us, ſafely kept, commended and honour'd through the whole Earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Againſt</hi> Petilian.</p>
                  <p>What has the Chair of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> done to thee, in which <hi>Peter</hi> ſat, and in which, at this day, <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> ſits; or of the Church of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in which <hi>James</hi> did ſit, and in which <hi>John</hi> does now ſit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Againſt</hi> Julian.</p>
                  <p>Irenaeus, Cyprian, Reticius, Olympius, Hilary, Gregory, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41791:30"/>John, Ambroſe—theſe were <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Grave, Learned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſtions upon the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Queſt. 35.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>King</hi> bears the Image of <hi>God,</hi> as the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore while he is in that Station, he is to be Honour'd, if not for himſelf, yet for his Order.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <head>St. Auguſtine <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Hippo</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> A. D. 420. Epiſtle 42.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Radix Chriſtianae Societatis per ſedes</hi> Apoſtolorum <hi>&amp; Succeſſiones</hi> Epiſcoporum <hi>certa per orbem Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagatione diffunditur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nemo ignorat Salvatorem</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copos <hi>Eccleſiis Inſtituiſſe; Ipſe enim priuſquam Coelos Aſcenderet, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens Manus</hi> Apoſtolis <hi>ordinavit eos</hi> Epiſcopos, <hi>Quod dixit</hi> Clarus à Muſcula <hi>in Concilio</hi> Carthag. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit</hi> Auguſt. <hi>de</hi> Baptiſmo <hi>contra</hi> Donatiſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Manifeſta eſt ſententia Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni noſtri</hi> Jeſu Chriſti <hi>Apoſtolos ſuos mittentis, &amp; ipſis ſolis Poteſtatem à Patre ſibi tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam permittentis; quibus nos
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:41791:29"/>nos Succeſſimus, eadem Poteſtate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam Domini Gubernantes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Divina voce ſub nomine Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li Laudatur Praepoſitus Eccleſiae.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>De verbis Domini, Serm.</hi> 24.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Si ſolis Apoſtolis dixit,</hi> Qui vos ſpernit, me ſpernit, <hi>ſpernite nos: Si autem Sermo Ejus pervenit ad nos, &amp; vocavit nos, &amp; in eorum loco Conſtituit nos, videte ne ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis nos.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Contra</hi> Fauſt. <hi>Lib.</hi> 33. <hi>cap.</hi> ult.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scripturam amplectimur quae ab Ipſius Preſentiae Chriſti temporibus, per Diſpenſationes Apoſtolorum, &amp; caeteras ab eorum ſedibus Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones Epiſcoporum, uſque ad haec tempora toto Orbe terrarum cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodita, commendata, clarificata per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>contra Literas Petiliani C.</hi> 51.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cathedra quid tibi fecit Eccleſiae</hi> Romanae <hi>in qua</hi> Petrus <hi>ſedit, &amp; in qua hodie</hi> Anaſtaſius <hi>ſedet; aut Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae</hi> Hieroſolimitanae <hi>in qua</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobus <hi>ſedit, &amp; in qua hodie</hi> Joan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <hi>ſedet.</hi> [<hi>Vid. contra</hi> Creſcon. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 37.]</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Contra</hi> Julianum, <hi>l.</hi> 2, <hi>cap.</hi> ult.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Irenaeus, Cyprianus, Reticius, Olympius, Hilarius, Gregorius,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41791:30"/>Baſilius, Joannes, Ambroſius, iſti erant Epiſcopi, Docti, Graves,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in Eccleſiae Regimine Clari.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quest. ex vet. Teſt. qu.</hi> 35.</p>
                  <p>Dei <hi>enim Imaginem habet</hi> Rex, <hi>ſicut &amp;</hi> Epiſcopus Chriſti. <hi>Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu ergo in ea traditione eſt, Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randus est, ſi non propter ſe, vel propter Ordinem.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Let this ſuffice as to the Teſtimonies of particular <hi>Fathers</hi> of the Church, tho' many more may be produc'd, in that compaſs of time, to which I have confin'd our preſent Inquiry. And now (that no Conviction might be wanting) I will ſet down ſome of the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Councils</hi> in thoſe times, to the ſame purpoſe; whereby it will appear, that <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as <hi>diſtinct</hi> from, and <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior</hi> to <hi>Presbytery,</hi> was not only the Judgment of the firſt Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but the current <hi>Doctrin,</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> both <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> in thoſe early Ages of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> the diſtinction of <hi>Biſhop, Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Deacon</hi> is ſo frequent, that it is almoſt in vain to give <hi>Citations.</hi> The 1ſt. and 2d. <hi>Can.</hi> ſhew the difference to be obſerv'd in the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining</hi> of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <p>Let a <hi>Biſhop</hi> be Conſecrated by two or three <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let a <hi>Presbyter</hi> and <hi>Deacon</hi> be Ordained by one <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>See the ſame Diſtinction of theſe Orders. <hi>Can.</hi> 3.4, 5, 6, 7, 8. 17, 18, 25. 27, 28, 29. 32 33. 36. 42. 44, 45. 51, 52, 53. 63. 68, 69, 70, 83. <hi>Can.</hi> 15. ſhews the Juriſdiction of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> over the <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If any <hi>Presbyter</hi> or <hi>Deacon,</hi> or any of the <hi>Clerical</hi> Order, ſhall leave his own Pariſh, and go to another, without the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s leave, he ſhall officiate no longer; eſpecially if he obey not the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> when he exhorts him to Return, perſiſting in his Inſolence
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:41791:30"/>and diſorderly Behaviour, but he ſhall be reduc'd there to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate only as a <hi>Lay-man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Can.</hi> 31. If any <hi>Presbyter,</hi> deſpiſing his own <hi>Biſhop,</hi> ſhall gather Congregations apart, and erect another Altar, his <hi>Biſhop</hi> not being Convict of Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Irreligion, let him be Depos'd as an Ambitious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for, he is a Tyrant: And likewiſe ſuch other <hi>Clergy</hi> or <hi>Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> who ſhall joyn themſelves to him ſhall be Excommunicated. But, let this be after the firſt, ſecond, and third Admonition of the <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 39. Let the <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> do nothing without the Conſent of the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> for it is He to whom the People of the Lord are committed, and from whom an account of their Souls will be Requir'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 41. We Ordain the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> to have power of the Goods of the Church—And to Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to thoſe who want, by the hands of the <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 55. If any <hi>Clergy man</hi> ſhall Reproach his <hi>Biſhop,</hi> let him be Depos'd: For, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak Evil of the Ruler of the People.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:41791:30"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:41791:30"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <p>After the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> I produce next a Great <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> of 87 Biſhops held at <hi>Carthage,</hi> in the Year of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 256, under St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> Archbiſhop of that Place, which is Publiſhed in St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Works before quoted, p. 229. where he tells us,</p>
                  <p>That beſides the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ther met there both <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> and great Numbers of the <hi>Laity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:41791:30"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epiſcopi plurimi cum Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris &amp; Diaconibus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:41791:31"/>
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Eliberis</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> about the Year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 305. Cap. 18. and 19.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Biſhops, Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> are Nam'd diſtinct. And c. 32. <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> are forbid to give the Communion to thoſe who had grievouſly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, without the Command of the Biſhop.</p>
                  <p>c. 75. Of thoſe who ſhall fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly accuſe a <hi>Biſhop, Presbyter,</hi> or <hi>Deacon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>c. 77. It is ordained that thoſe who are Baptiz'd by a <hi>Deacon,</hi> without the <hi>Riſhop</hi> or <hi>Presbyter,</hi> ſhall afterwards be Confirm'd by the <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Eliberis</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> about the Year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 305. Cap. 18. and 19.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Epiſcopi, Presbyteri, &amp; Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Non eſt Presbyterorum, aut Diaconorum Communionem ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus praeſtare debere, niſi eis juſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Epiſcopus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Si quis Epiſcopum, Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, vel Diaconum falſis Crimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus appetierit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Si quis Diaconus, ſine Epiſcopo vel Presbytero aliquos Baptizave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; Epiſcopus eos per Benedictio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem perficere debebit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Arles</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> about the Year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 309. c. 18. It is ordain'd that the <hi>Deacons</hi> ſhou'd be ſubject to the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters:</hi> And c. 19.</head>
                  <p>That the <hi>Presbyters</hi> ſhou'd be ſubject to their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and do nothing without his conſent.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Arles</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> about the Year of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 309. c. 18. It is ordain'd that the <hi>Deacons</hi> ſhou'd be ſubject to the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters:</hi> And c. 19.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Presbyteri ſine Conſcientia Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi nihil faciant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Ancyra,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A. D 315.</note> A. D. 315.</head>
                  <p>c. 1. and 2. Having Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thoſe <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> who had, in times of Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Offer'd to Idols, from the Execution of their Office, <hi>ſays,</hi> that notwithſtanding the <hi>Biſhop</hi> may Diſpence with them if he ſees their Repentance ſincere; for that this Power is lodg'd in the <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Ancyra,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A. D 315.</note> A. D. 315.</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A. D. 321.</note> A. D. 321.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 41. That no <hi>Clergy-man</hi> ought to Travel, without the conſent of his <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 56. That the <hi>Presbyters</hi> ought not to go into the Church, and ſit in their Stales, till the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> come, and to go in with the <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Laodicea,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A. D. 321.</note> A. D. 321.</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41791:31"/>
                  <head>The Firſt and Great Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> A. D. 325.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 16. That if any <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> or <hi>Deacons</hi> leave their own Churches, they ought not to be receiv'd into another Church: And that if any ſhall ordain ſuch in his Ch. as belong to another, without the conſent of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Biſhop,</hi> let ſuch Ordination be void.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <head>The Firſt and Great Council of <hi>Nice,</hi> A. D. 325.</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Gangra,</hi> 326.
<note place="margin">A. D. 326.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 6. If any have private Meetings out of the Church, without their <hi>Preshyter,</hi> let 'em be Anathematiz'd by the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 7. If any will take or give of the Fruits offer'd to the Church, out of the Church, without leave of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> let him be <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Gangra,</hi> 326.
<note place="margin">A. D. 326.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Antioch,</hi> A. D. 341.
<note place="margin">A. D. 341.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 3. If any <hi>Presbyter</hi> or <hi>Deacon,</hi> leaving his own Pariſh, ſhall go to others; and refuſe to return, when his own <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſhall ſummon him, let him be Depos'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 4. If any <hi>Biſhop</hi> being Depos'd by a <hi>Synod,</hi> or a <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> or <hi>Deacon</hi> being Depos'd by his own proper <hi>Biſhop,</hi> ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to exerciſe his Function, let no room be left them, either for Reſtauration or Apology.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 5. If any <hi>Presbyter</hi> or <hi>Deacon,</hi> deſpiſing his own <hi>Biſhop,</hi> ſhall ſeparate himſelf from the Church, and gather a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41791:32"/>of his own, and ſet up a different Altar; and ſhall refuſe to ſubmit himſelf to his <hi>Biſhop,</hi> calling him the firſt and ſecond time, let him be abſolutely Depos'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 12. If any <hi>Presbyter</hi> or <hi>Deacon,</hi> being Depos'd by his own proper <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or a <hi>Biſhop</hi> by the <hi>Synod,</hi> dare Appeal to the <hi>King,</hi> ſeeing his Appeal lies to a greater <hi>Synod</hi> of more <hi>Biſhops,</hi> where he is to expect the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of his Cauſe, and to teſerr the Deciſion to them; But if, making light of theſe, he trouble the <hi>King</hi> with it, ſuch an one is worthy of no Pardon, nor ought to be admitted to make any ſort of Apology, or to have hopes of his being ever Reſtor'd any more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 22. That a <hi>Biſhop</hi> ought not to Ordain <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> in another <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s Dioceſs, without his leave.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41791:31"/>
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Antioch,</hi> A. D. 341.
<note place="margin">A. D. 341.</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:41791:32"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>In the Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> A. D. 348.</head>
                  <p>C. xi. The Caſe is put where a <hi>Deacon</hi> being accus'd, ſhall be Try'd by <hi>three</hi> Neighbouring <hi>Biſhops,</hi> a <hi>Presbyter</hi> by <hi>ſix,</hi> and a <hi>Biſhop</hi> by <hi>twelve.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" type="section">
                  <head>In the Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> A. D. 348.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A tribus vicinis Epiſcopis, ſi Diaconus eſt arguatur; ſi Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, à ſex, ſi Epiſcopus à duedecim Conſacerdotibus audiatur.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond <hi>Oecumenical Council</hi> of <hi>Conſtantineple,</hi> A. D. 381.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 6. Ranks thoſe with <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks,</hi> who, tho' they proſeſs the true Faith, yet run into <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and gather Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons apart from, and in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to our Canonied <hi>Biſhops.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond <hi>Oecumenical Council</hi> of <hi>Conſtantineple,</hi> A. D. 381.</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> A. D. 419.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 3. Mentions the three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41791:32"/>
                     <hi>Orders</hi> of <hi>Biſhop, Presbyter,</hi> and <hi>Deacon;</hi> and compares them to the <hi>High-Prieſt, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Levites.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the ſame manner they are as diſtinctly mention'd,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 4. <hi>Biſhop, Presbyter</hi> and <hi>Deacon;</hi> and their Powers di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. For,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 6. It is declar'd not to be lawful for <hi>Presbyters</hi> to <hi>Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate Churches,</hi> or Reconcile <hi>Penitents;</hi> but if any be in great Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and deſirous to be Reconcil'd in the abſence of the <hi>Biſhop,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Presbyter</hi> ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and receive his Orders in it, as is declar'd in the 7. <hi>Can.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 10. If any <hi>Presbyter,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing puff'd up with Pride, ſhall make a <hi>Schiſm</hi> againſt his own proper <hi>Biſhop,</hi> let him be <hi>Anathema.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 11. Gives leave to a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> who is Condemn'd by his <hi>Biſhop,</hi> to Appeal to the Neighbouring <hi>Biſhops;</hi> but if, without this, he flies off, and makes a <hi>Schiſm</hi> from his <hi>Biſhop,</hi> it confirms the <hi>Anathema</hi> upon him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 12. Orders what is before Recited out of <hi>Can.</hi> xi. of the Council of <hi>Carthage.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That a <hi>Biſhop</hi> who is Accus'd ſhall be try'd by <hi>twelve Biſhops,</hi> if more may not be had; a <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter</hi> by <hi>ſix Biſhops,</hi> with his own <hi>Biſhop;</hi> and a <hi>Deacon</hi> by <hi>three.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 14. Orders that in <hi>Tripeli,</hi> becauſe of the ſmaller num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Biſhops</hi> in thoſe Parts, a <hi>Presbyter</hi> ſhall be judg'd by <hi>Five Biſhops,</hi> and a <hi>Deacon</hi> by <hi>Three,</hi> his own proper <hi>Biſhop</hi> Preſiding.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 46. That a <hi>Presbyter</hi> ſhall not Reconcile a Penitent, without the knowledge of the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> unleſs upon neceſſity, in the abſence of the <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41791:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 59. That one <hi>Biſhop</hi> may ordain many <hi>Presbyters;</hi> but that it was hard to find a <hi>Presbyter</hi> who was fit to be made a <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 65. That a <hi>Clergy man,</hi> being Condemned by the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> cannot be deliver'd by that <hi>Church</hi> to which he did belong, or by any Man whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 126. That <hi>Presbyters</hi> and <hi>Deacons</hi> may Appeal from their own <hi>Biſhop</hi> to the Neighbouring <hi>Biſhops,</hi> choſen by conſent of their own <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and from them to the <hi>Primate</hi> or <hi>Provincial Synod;</hi> but not to any <hi>Trans-marine</hi> or <hi>Forraign</hi> Juriſdiction, under pain of Excommunication.</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:41791:32"/>
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> A. D. 419.</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:41791:32"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41791:33"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="eng" type="section">
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> being the Fourth General Council <hi>A. D.</hi> 451.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 9. If any <hi>Clergy-man</hi> have a Cauſe of complaint againſt another <hi>Clergy-man,</hi> let him not leave his own proper <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> and have Recourſe to the <hi>Secular</hi> Courts-Whoever does otherwiſe ſhall be put under the Canonical Cenſures.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 13. That a Forreign <hi>Clergy-man,</hi> and not known, ſhall not officiate in another City, without Commendatory Letters from his own <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:41791:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 18. If any of the <hi>Clergy</hi> ſhall be found Conſpiring, or Joyning in <hi>Fraternities,</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving any thing againſt the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> they ſhall fall from their own Degree.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 29. To reduce a <hi>Biſhop</hi> to the Degree of a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> is <hi>Sacrilege.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="grc" type="section">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:41791:33"/>
                  <head>The Council of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> being the Fourth General Council <hi>A. D.</hi> 451.</head>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:41791:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Theſe Authorities are ſo plain and full as to prevent any Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, or Multiplying of further Quotations, which might eaſily be done: For, if theſe can be anſwer'd, ſo may all that can poſſibly be produc'd, or framed in words.</p>
                  <p>And ther is no Remedy left to the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and other Diſſenters from <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> but to deny all theſe by whole-ſale, to throw off all <hi>Antiquity,</hi> as well the firſt Ages of Chriſtianity, even that wherein the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves Liv'd and Taught, as all ſince; and to ſtand upon a New Foundation of their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention.</p>
                  <p>But this only ſhews the Deſperatneſs of their Cauſe; and the Impregnable Bulwork of <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> which (I muſt ſay it) ſtands upon ſo <hi>Many, Clear,</hi> and <hi>Authentick Evidences,</hi> as can never be overthrown, but by ſuch <hi>Topicks</hi> as muſt render <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelf Precarious.</p>
                  <p>And if from the <hi>Etymology</hi> of the Words <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter,</hi> any Argument can be drawn (againſt all the Authorities Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd) to prove them the ſame, we may, by this way of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, prove <hi>Cyrus</hi> to be <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for ſo he is call'd, <hi>Iſa.</hi> XLV. 1.</p>
                  <p>Or if the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will have their <hi>Moderator</hi> to be a <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop,</hi> we will not Quarrel with them about a word. Let us then have a <hi>Moderator,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Biſhops</hi> before deſcrib'd, <hi>viz.</hi> A <hi>Moderator,</hi> as a ſtanding Officer, during <hi>Life,</hi> to whom all the <hi>Presbyters</hi> are to be obedient as to <hi>Chriſt, i. e.</hi> to the <hi>Moderator,</hi> as Repreſenting the Perſon of <hi>Christ:</hi> That nothing be done in the <hi>Church</hi> without Him: That He be underſtood as the <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>Unity</hi> in His <hi>Church;</hi> ſo that, they who unjuſtly break off from his <hi>Communion,</hi> are thereby in a <hi>Schiſm:</hi> That he ſhew his <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> by Regular Ordination, convey'd down from the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> In ſhort, that He have all that <hi>Character</hi> and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41791:34"/>
                     <hi>Authority,</hi> which we ſee to have been Recogniz'd in the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> in the very Age of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and all the ſucceeding Ages of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> and then call Him <hi>Moderator, Superintendent,</hi> or <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop:</hi> For, the Conteſt is not about the <hi>Name,</hi> but the <hi>Thing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And if we go only upon the <hi>Etymology</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> how ſhall we prove <hi>Presbyters</hi> to be an <hi>Order</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> more than <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops?</hi> as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſaid to <hi>Dracontius</hi> of thoſe who perſuaded him not to accept of a <hi>Biſhoprick.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q xml:lang="eng">
                     <hi>Why do they perſuade you not to be a Biſhop, when they themſelves will have Presbyters?</hi>
                  </q>
                  <q xml:lang="grc">
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>I will end this Head, with the Advice of that great <hi>Father</hi> to this ſame <hi>Drasontius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>If the Government of the Churches do not pleaſe you; and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t you think the Office of a <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> has no Reward, thereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your ſelf a Deſpiſer of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> who did Inſtitute it; I beſeech you ſurmiſe not any ſuch things as theſe, nor do you Entertain any who adviſe ſuch things; for that is not worthy of <hi>Dracontius:</hi> For what things the Lord did Inſtitute by His <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> thoſe things remain both good and ſure.</q>
                  <q xml:lang="grc">
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Athanaſ.</hi> Epiſt. ad <hi>Dracont.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p n="2">II. Having thus Explain'd thoſe Texts of <hi>Scripture</hi> which ſpeak of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> by the Concurrent ſenſe of thoſe who liv'd with the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and were taught the Faith from their Mouths; who liv'd zealous <hi>Confeſſors,</hi> and dy'd glorious <hi>Martyrs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and who Succeeded the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in thoſe very <hi>Churches</hi> where them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves had ſat <hi>Biſhops:</hi> And having deduc'd their Teſtimonies, and of thoſe who Succeeded them down for Four Hundred and Fifty Years after <hi>Chriſt</hi> (from which time, ther is no doubt rais'd againſt the Univerſal Reception of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi>) and this not only from their <hi>Writings</hi> apact, but by their <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> when Aſſembl'd together in <hi>Council;</hi> which one wou'd think ſufficient Evidence, againſt none at all on the other ſide, that is, for the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:41791:34"/>
                     <hi>Churches</hi> in the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Form, of which no one Inſtance can be given, ſo much as of any one <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>World</hi> ſo Deduc'd, not only from the days of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> (as is ſhewn for <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi>) but before <hi>Calvin,</hi> and thoſe who <hi>Reform'd</hi> with him, about 160 Years laſt paſt: I ſay, tho' what is done is ſufficient to ſatisfie any <hi>Indifferent</hi> and <hi>Un-byaſs'd</hi> Judgment, yet ther is one <hi>Topick</hi> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, which, with our <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> weighs more than all <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councils;</hi> and that is, the late <hi>Reſormation,</hi> from whence ſome Date their very <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> And if even by this too <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> ſhou'd be <hi>Witneſſed</hi> and <hi>Approv'd,</hi> then is ther nothing at all in the World left to the Oppoſers of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> nothing of <hi>Antiquity, Precedent,</hi> or any <hi>Authority</hi> but their own <hi>Wilful Will</hi> againſt all <hi>Ages</hi> of the whole <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> even that of the <hi>Reformation</hi> as well as all the Reſt.</p>
                  <p>Let us then Examine. Firſt, for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that is thrown off clearly by our <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> for that was <hi>Reform'd</hi> under <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> and continues ſo to this day.</p>
                  <p>And as to our Neighbour Nation of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> do boaſt that the <hi>Reformation</hi> was made by <hi>Presbyters;</hi> that is moſt <hi>Clearly</hi> and <hi>Authentically</hi> Confuted by a Late Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and worthy Author (already mention'd) in his <hi>Fundamental Charter of Presbytery,</hi> Printed 1695. ſo as to ſtop the Mouths of the moſt Perverſe, who will not be Perſuaded tho' they are Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded.</p>
                  <p>Go we then abroad, and ſee the ſtate of the <hi>Reformed</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches there.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lutherans</hi> are all cut off, as the Church of <hi>England;</hi> for they ſtill Retain <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as in <hi>Denmark, Sweden,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Ther remains now only the <hi>Calviniſts.</hi> Here it is the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> ſet up their Reſt! This is their ſtrong <hi>Foundation!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And this will fail them as much as all the other: For, be it known unto them (however they will receive it) that <hi>Calvin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and <hi>Beza,</hi> and the reſt of the Learned <hi>Reformers</hi> of their Part, did give their Teſtimony for <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> as much as any. They counted it a moſt unjuſt <hi>Reproach</hi> upon them, to think that they condemn'd <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> which they ſay they did not throw off, but cou'd not have it there, in <hi>Geneva,</hi> without coming under the <hi>Papal Hierarchy:</hi> They highly <hi>Applanded</hi> and <hi>Congratulated</hi> the <hi>Epiſcopal Hierarchy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41791:35"/>Letters to Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to the <hi>Arch-biſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of our <hi>Eagliſh Biſhips:</hi> They Pray'd heartily to God for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance and Preſervation of it: Bemoan'd their own unhappy Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, that they cou'd not have the like, becauſe they had no <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to Protect them; and wiſhed for <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> in their <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> the want of which they own'd as a great <hi>Defec t;</hi> but call'd it their <hi>Misfortune</hi> rather than their <hi>Fault.</hi> As the Learned of the <hi>French Hagonots</hi> have likewiſe pleaded on their Behalf.</p>
                  <p>As for their <hi>Excuſe.</hi> I do not now meddle with it, for I think it was not a good one. They might have had <hi>Biſhops</hi> from other Places, tho' ther were none among themſelves, but thoſe who were <hi>Popiſh:</hi> And they might as well have had <hi>Biſhops</hi> as <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> without the Countenance of the <hi>Civil-Magiſtrate.</hi> It might have rais'd a greater <hi>Perſecution</hi> againſt them; but that is nothing as to the <hi>Truth</hi> of the thing. And if they thought it a <hi>Truth,</hi> they ought to have <hi>ſuffer'd</hi> for it.</p>
                  <p>But whatever becomes of their <hi>Excuſe,</hi> here it is plain, that they gave their <hi>Suffrage</hi> for <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> which who ſo pleaſes may ſee at large in Dr. <hi>Durel's View of the Government and Worſhip in the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches beyond the Seas,</hi> (who was himſelf one of them) Printed. 1662.</p>
                  <p>So that our Modern <hi>Presbyterians</hi> have departed from <hi>Clavin</hi> as well as from <hi>Luther,</hi> in their Abhorrence of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> from all the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, in all Ages; and particularly from all our late <hi>Reformers,</hi> both of one ſort and other.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Calvin</hi> wou'd have <hi>Anathematiz'd</hi> all of them, had he liv'd in our times. He ſay's ther were none ſuch to be found in his time, who oppos'd the <hi>Epiſcopal Hierarchy,</hi> but only the <hi>Papal,</hi> which Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pir'd to an <hi>Univerſal Supremacy</hi> in the <hi>See</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> over the whole <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> which is the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone. But, ſays he,</p>
                  <q xml:lang="eng">If they wou'd give us ſuch a <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> in which the <hi>Biſhops</hi> ſhou'd ſo Excell, as that they did not refuſe to be ſubject to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to depend upon Him, as their <hi>only</hi> Head, and refer all to Him; then I will confeſs that they are worthy of all <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themas,</hi> if any ſuch ſhall be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41791:35"/>found, who will not Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence it, and ſubmit themſelves to it, with the utmoſt Obedience.</q>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:41791:35"/>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">
                     <hi>Talem ſi nobis Hierarchiam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibeant, in qua ſic Emineant</hi> Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi, <hi>ut Chriſto ſubeſſe non Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, &amp; ab Illo ranquam unico Capite pendeant, &amp; ad Ipſum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferantur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Tum vero nullo non Anathemate dignos fatear ſi qui erunt qui non Eam Reverean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſummaque Obedientia obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:41791:35"/>Calvin. De neceſſitat. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claeſ. Reformand.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>See, he ſays, <hi>ſi qui erunt,</hi> if ther ſhall be any ſuch, which ſuppoſes that he knew none ſuch; and that he own'd none ſuch amongſt his <hi>Reformers:</hi> And that if ever any ſuch ſhou'd ariſe, he thought ther were no <hi>Anathemas</hi> which they did not deſerve, who ſhou'd refuſe to ſubmit to the <hi>Epiſcopal Hierarchy,</hi> without ſuch an <hi>Univerſal Head,</hi> as Excludes <hi>Chriſt</hi> from being the <hi>only</hi> Univerſal <hi>Head;</hi> for if ther be <hi>another,</hi> (tho <hi>ſubſtitute</hi>) He is not <hi>only.</hi> Thus He is called the <hi>Chief Biſhop,</hi> but never the <hi>only Biſhop,</hi> becauſe ther are others deputed under Him. But He calls no <hi>Biſhop</hi> the <hi>Univerſal Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> becauſe He has appointed no <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute</hi> in that <hi>ſupreme</hi> Office; as not of <hi>Univerſal King,</hi> ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Univerſal Biſhop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>Beza</hi> ſuppoſes as Poſitively as <hi>Calvin</hi> had done, that ther were none who did oppoſe the <hi>Epiſcopal Hierarchy</hi> without ſuch an <hi>Univerſal Head</hi> now upon Earth; or that oppos'd the <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy;</hi> and condemns them as <hi>Mad-men,</hi> if any ſuch cou'd be found. For thus ſays he,</p>
                  <q xml:lang="eng">If ther be any (which you ſhall hardly peſwade me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) who reject the whole Order of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> God forbid that any Man, in his wits, ſhou'd aſſent to the <hi>Madneſs</hi> of ſuch Men.</q>
                  <q xml:lang="lat">
                     <hi>Si qui ſunt autem (quod ſane mihi non facile perſuaſeris) qui omnem Epiſcoporum ordinem Rejiciant, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit ut quiſquam ſatis ſanae mentis furoribus illorum aſſentiatur. Beza. ad Tractat. de Miniſtr. Ev. Grad. ab Hadrian. Sarav. Belga Editam. c.</hi> 1.</q>
                  <p>And particularly as to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and her <hi>Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> of <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> he ſays, 
<q xml:lang="eng">that he never meant to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne any thing of that; but calls it a <hi>ſingular Bleſſing of God;</hi> and <hi>wiſhes that ſhe may ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy it.</hi>
                     </q>
                     <q xml:lang="lat">
                        <hi>Fruatur ſane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>la ſingulari Dei beneficentia, quae utinam ſit illi Perpetua.</hi> Ibid. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that our Modern <hi>Presbyterians</hi> are diſarm'd of the Precedent of <hi>Calvin, Beza,</hi> and all the <hi>Reformers</hi> abroad; by whoſe Sentence they are <hi>Anathematiz'd,</hi> and counted as <hi>Mad-men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here then, let us conſider and beware of the Fatal Progreſs of <hi>Error! Calvin</hi> and the <hi>Reformers</hi> with him, ſet up <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as they pretended, by <hi>Neceſſity;</hi> but ſtill kept up and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41791:36"/>Profeſs'd the higheſt Regard to the <hi>Epiſcopal Character</hi> and <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity:</hi> But thoſe who pretend to follow their Example, have utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Abdicated the whole <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as <hi>Anti-Chriſtian</hi> and an <hi>Inſupportable Grievance!</hi> While, at the ſame time, they wou'd ſeem to pay the greateſt Reverence to theſe <hi>Reformers;</hi> and much more to the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>First</hi> and <hi>Purest</hi> Ages of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> whoſe <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councils</hi> ſpoke all the <hi>High</hi> things, before Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in behalf of <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> far beyond the <hi>Language</hi> of our later <hi>Apologiſts</hi> for that <hi>Hierarchy;</hi> or what durſt now be Repeated, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept from ſuch <hi>unqueſtionable Authority.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this they imitate the hardneſs of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who Built the <hi>Sepulchers</hi> of thoſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> whom their <hi>Fathers</hi> ſlew; while, at the ſame time, they Adher'd to, and out did the Wickedneſs of their <hi>Fathers,</hi> in Perſecuting the <hi>Succeſſors</hi> of thoſe <hi>Prophets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 3. col. 2. l. 11. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 39. col. 1. l. 10, 11. r. All of you follow your Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. col. 2. <hi>penult.</hi> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 40. l. 16. A. D. 180. ſhou'd be on the Margent; p. 42. col. 2. l. 3. dele—after <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. and r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 44. col. 2. l. 14. r. Ira. p. 45. col. 2. l. 28. r. <hi>ſcripturarum.</hi> p. 47. col. 2. <hi>penult.</hi> r. <hi>ad Heliodorum.</hi> p. 51. col. 1. l. 11, 12, 13, 14. r. As likewiſe ſuch other <hi>Clergy,</hi> and as many as ſhall join with him: but the <hi>Lay-men</hi> ſhall be Excommunicated.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="disclaimer">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:41791:36"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>WHereas I have plac'd the <hi>Apoſtolical Canons</hi> in the Front of the <hi>Councils</hi> before Quoted, I thought fit (to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent needleſs Cavil) to give this Advertiſement, that I do not contend, they were made by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves; but by the Holy <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> about the end of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> and beginning of the <hi>Third Century,</hi> as a <hi>Summary</hi> of that <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> which had been tranſmitted to them, by Un-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Tradition, from the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> whence they have juſtly obtain'd the Name of <hi>The Apoſtolical Canons;</hi> and, as ſuch, have been Receiv'd and Reverenc'd in the ſucceeding Ages of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Councils</hi> Quoted after theſe <hi>Canons,</hi> bear their Proper Dates; and ther can be no Conteſt about them.</p>
            <p>And what is Quoted of St. <hi>Ignatius</hi> and the other <hi>Fathers,</hi> is from the moſt Uncontroverted Parts of their Works, to obviate the Objection of <hi>Interpolations,</hi> and <hi>Additions,</hi> by the Noiſe of which our Adverſaries endeavour to throw off, or enervate their whole Authority; and quite to diſ-arm us of all that <hi>Light</hi> which we have from the <hi>Primitive Ages</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it makes all againſt them. Though they fail not to Quote the <hi>Fathers</hi> on their ſide, whenſoever they can Screw them to give the leaſt ſeeming Countenance to their <hi>Novelties</hi> and <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors:</hi> Yet <hi>Boldly</hi> Reject them All, when brought in Evidence againſt them, and that they can no otherwiſe ſtruggle from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the weight of their Authority.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of Books Printed for</hi> Charles Brome <hi>at the</hi> Gun <hi>at the Weſt-End, of St.</hi> Paul'<hi>s</hi> Church-yard.</head>
            <p>THE Snake in the Graſs: Or, Satan transform'd into an Angel of Light. Diſcovering the Deep and Unſuſpected Subtilty which is couched under the Pretended Simplicity of many of the Principal Leaders of thoſe People call'd Quakers. The Second Edition, with Additions.</p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:41791:37"/>
            <p>Some Seaſonable Reflections upon the Quakers Solemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation againſt <hi>George Keith</hi>'s Proceedings at <hi>Turner's-Hall,</hi> 29. <hi>April</hi> 1697. Which was by them Printed, and ſent thither, as the Reaſons of their not Appearing to defend themſelves. Herein annex'd Verbatim By an Impartial Hand.</p>
            <p>Satan Diſ-rob'd from his Diſguiſe of Light: Or, the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Laſt Shift to Cover their Monſtrous Hereſies, laid fully o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. In a Reply to <hi>Thomas Ellwood</hi>'s Anſwer (Publiſhed the End of laſt Mouth) to <hi>George Keith</hi>'s Narrative of the Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings at <hi>Turner's-Hall, June</hi> 11. 1696. Which alſo may ſerve for a Reply (as to the main Points of Doctrine) to <hi>Geo. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi>'s Anſwer to The Snake in the Graſs; to be Publiſhed the End of next Month, if this prevent it not.</p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe proving the Divine Inſtitution of Water-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: Wherein the Quaker-Arguments againſt it, are Collected and Confuted. With as much as is needful concerning the Lord's Supper. Theſe Four Books are Written by the Author of The Snake in the Graſs.</p>
            <p>The Quakers ſet in their True Light, in order to give the Nation a clear ſight of what they hold concerning Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> the Scriptures, Water-Baptiſm, the Lord's Supper, Magiſtracy, Miniſtry, Laws, and Government: Hiſtorically col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected out of their moſt approved Authors, which are their beſt Conſtruing-Books, from the year of their Riſe 1650, to the year of their Progreſs 1696. By <hi>Francis Bugg,</hi> Sen.</p>
            <p>An Eſſay concerning Preaching: Written for the Direction of a Young Divine; and uſeful alſo for the People, in order to Profitable Hearing.</p>
            <p>Crums of Comfort, and Godly Prayers; With Thankful Remembrances of God's wonderful Deliverances of this Land.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41791:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
